<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Solomons recantation, entituled Ecclesiastes, paraphrased. With a soliloquie or meditation upon every chapter. / By Francis Quarles. Opus posthumum. Never before printed. With a short relation of his life and death.</title>
            <author>Quarles, Francis, 1592-1644.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91574</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Q116</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E284_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200060</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860864</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860864</idno>
            <idno type="VID">158496</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91574)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158496)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 47:E284[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Solomons recantation, entituled Ecclesiastes, paraphrased. With a soliloquie or meditation upon every chapter. / By Francis Quarles. Opus posthumum. Never before printed. With a short relation of his life and death.</title>
                  <author>Quarles, Francis, 1592-1644.</author>
                  <author>Quarles, Ursula, b. 1601.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 62, [2] p. : ill., port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.F. for Richard Royston, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Angel in Ivie-Lane.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A short relation of the life and death of Mr. Francis Quarles" is by Ursula Quarles, his widow.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 15th.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ecclesiastes --  Paraphrases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:158496:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>Effigies Franciſci Quarles.</p>
                  <p>Aetatis Suae 52.</p>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Francis Quarles</figDesc>
                  <q>
                     <l>Pictor adumbravit Vultum guem cernimus, aſt hic</l>
                     <l>Non valet egregias pingere mentis Opes.</l>
                     <l>Has siſcire cupis, sua consule Carmina, in illis</l>
                     <l>Dotes percipies pectoris eximias.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>What heere wee ſee is but a <hi>Graven</hi> face.</l>
                     <l>Onely the <hi>ſhaddow</hi> of that brittle caſe</l>
                     <l>Wherin were treaſur'd up those <hi>Gemms,</hi> which he</l>
                     <l>Hath loft behind him to Posteritie.</l> 
                     <bibl>Al: Roſs.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <byline>W. M ſculp:</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:158496:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SOLOMONS</hi> RECANTATION, ENTITULED ECCLESIASTES, PARAPHRASED.</p>
            <p>VVith a SOLILOQUIE or Meditation upon every Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Very Seaſonable and Vſefull for theſe Times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By FRANCIS QUARLES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Opus poſthumum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Never before Imprinted.</p>
            <p>WITH A SHORT RELATION OF HIS Life and Death.</p>
            <q>O curas hominum! O quantum eſt in rebus inane!</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for <hi>Richard Royſton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the Signe of the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Ivie-Lane.</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb facs="tcp:158496:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:158496:2"/>
            <head>A SHORT RELATION OF THE Life and Death of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Francis Quarles,</hi> by <hi>Vrſula Quarles,</hi> his ſorrowfull Widow.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough it be inconſiſtent with the duty of a wife, to be injurious in any reſpect to her husband; yet in this my bold undertaking I fear I ſhall be ſo to mine: which I doubt not but he would have forgiven, if he had been living, as proceeding from love; and I hope his friends will pardon (now he is dead) as being the laſt duty I can perform to a loving husband. Thoſe that ſee with what pen his Works are written, will ſay his life deſerved a more skilfull Artiſt to ſet it forth: which office though many might have been procured to undertake; and to which I doubt not, but ſome would voluntarily have offered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if they had known that ſuch a thing had been inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: yet have I (with much zeal, though ſmall diſcretion) adventured upon it my ſelf, as being fully aſſured that none can be more ſenſible of the loſſe of him, then I, though thouſands might have expreſt that loſſe to the world with more Art and better judgement.</p>
            <p>He was a Gentleman both by birth and deſert: deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of an ancient Family, and yet (which is rare in theſe laſt and worſt times) he was an ornament to his Anceſtors. His Father was <hi>James Quarles</hi> of Rumford Eſquire, Clerk of the Green-cloth and Purveyor of the Navie to Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and yonger brother to Sir <hi>Robert Quarles.</hi> His education was ſuitable to his birth; firſt, at ſchoole in the
<pb facs="tcp:158496:3"/>Countrey, where his ſchool-fellows will ſay, he ſurpaſſed all his equals; afterward at Chriſts Colledge in Cambridge, where how he profited, I am not able to judge, but am ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſured by men of much learning and judgement, that his Works in very many places doe ſufficiently teſtifie more then ordinary fruits of his Univerſity ſtudies. Laſt of all, he was tranſplanted from thence to Lincolns Inne, where for ſome yeares he ſtudied the Laws of England; not ſo much out of deſire to benefit himſelf thereby, as his friends and neighbours (ſhewing therein his continuall inclination to peace) by compoſing ſuits &amp; differences amongſt them.</p>
            <p>After he came to maturity, he was not deſirous to put himſelf into the world, otherwiſe he might have had grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter preferments then he had: He was neither ſo unfit for Court preferment, nor ſo ill beloved there, but that he might have raiſed his fortunes thereby, if he had had any inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that way. But his mind was chiefly ſet upon his devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſtudy: yet not altogether ſo much, but that he faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſcharged the place of Cup-bearer to the Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the office of Secretary to the Reverend and Learned Lord Primate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that now is, and of Chronologer to the famous City of London; which place he held to his death, and would have given that City (and the world) a teſtimony that he was their faithfull ſervant therein, if it had pleaſed God to bleſſe him with life to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect what he had begun. He was the husband of one wife, by whom he was the father of eighteen children, and how faithfull and loving a husband and father he was, the joynt tears of his widow and fatherleſſe children will better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe then my pen is able to doe.</p>
            <p>In all his duties to God and Man he was conſcionable and orderly: He preferred God and Religion to the firſt place in his thoughts, his King and Country to the ſecond, his family and ſtudies he reſerved to the laſt. As for God, he was frequent in his devotions and prayers to him, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt conſtant in reading or meditating on his holy Word, as his <hi>Divine Fancies</hi> and other parts of his Works will ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently teſtifie. For his Religion, he was a true ſonne of the Church of England; an even Proteſtant, not in the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
<pb facs="tcp:158496:3"/>biaſſed to this hand of ſuperſtition, or that of ſchiſme, though both thoſe factions were ready to cry him down for his inclination to the contrary. His love to his King and Country in theſe late unhappy times of diſtraction, was manifeſt, in that he uſed his pen and powred out his conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall prayers and tears to quench this miſerable fire of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention, while too many others added daily fewell unto it. And for his family, his care was very great over that, even then, when his occaſions cauſed his abſence from it. And when he was at home, his exhortations to us to continue in vertue and godly life, were ſo pious and frequent; his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions ſo grave and piercing; his reprehenſions ſo mild and gentle, and (above all) his own example in every reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and morall duty, ſo conſtant and manifeſt, that his equall may be deſired, but can hardly be met withall.</p>
            <p>Neither was his good example of a godly life contained only within his own family: others as well as we have (or at leaſt might have) made good uſe of it. For he was not addicted to any notorious vice whatſoever: He was cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and affable to all; moderate and diſcreet in all his actions: And though it be too frequent a fault (as we ſee by experience) in Gentlemen whoſe diſpoſitions incline them to the ſtudy of Poetry, to be looſe and debauch'd in their lives and converſations; yet was it very far from him: Their delight could not be greater in the Tavern, then his was in his Study; to which he devoted himſelf late and early, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually by three a clock in the morning. The fruits thereof are beſt taſted by thoſe, who have moſt peruſed his Works, and therefore I ſhall be ſilent in that particular. For though it had been neceſſary in any other, to have ſpoken ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of his writings; yet I hope it will not be expected from me, ſeeing that neither the judgement of my ſex can be thought competent, nor (if it were) would the nearneſs of my relation to him ſuffer me to praiſe that, at commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations whereof from others, I have often bluſhed.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore rather deſire leave to ſpeak a work or two concerning the bleſſed end of my dear husband, which was every way anſwerable to his godly life; or rather (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) ſurpaſſed it. For, as gold is purified in the fire, ſo were
<pb facs="tcp:158496:4"/>all his Chriſtian vertues more refined and remarkable du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of his ſickneſſe.</p>
            <p>His patience was wouderfull, inſomuch as he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe no pain, even then when all his friends perceived his diſeaſe to be mortall; but ſtill rendred thanks to God for his eſpeciall love to him, <hi>in taking him into his own hands to chastiſe, while others were expoſed to the fury of their enemies, the power of piſtols, and the trampling of horſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He expreſt great ſorrow for his ſins, and when it was told him, that his friends conceived he did thereby much harm to himſelfe: he anſwered, <hi>They were not his friends, that would not give him leave to be penitent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Exhortations to his friends that came to viſit him were moſt divine; wiſhing them <hi>to have a care of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of their time, and every day to call themſelves to an accompt, that ſo when they come to their bed of ſickneſſe, they might lie upon it with a rejoycing heart.</hi> And doubtleſſe ſuch an one was his: Inſomuch as he thanked God, that whereas he might have juſtly expected, that <hi>his conſcience ſhould look him in the face like a Lyon, it rather looked upon him like a Lamb:</hi> and that <hi>God had forgiven him his ſins, and that night ſealed him his pardon:</hi> And many other heavenly expreſſions to the like effect. I might here add what bleſſed advice he gave to me in particular, <hi>ſtill to truſt in God, whoſe promiſe is, to provide for the Widow and Fatherleſſe, &amp;c.</hi> but this is already imprinted in my heart; and therefore I ſhall not need here again to inſert it.</p>
            <p>His charity was extraordinary, in freely forgiving his greateſt enemies, even thoſe who were the cauſe of his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and by conſequence of his death. For, whereas a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition full of unjuſt aſperſions, was preferred againſt him by eight men, (whereof he knew not any two, nor they him, ſave only by ſight) the firſt news of it ſtruck him ſo to the heart, that he never recovered it, but ſaid plainly, <hi>it would be his death.</hi> And when his friends (to comfort him) told him that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>I. S.</hi> (the chief promoter thereof) was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to an accompt for it, and would goe neer to be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; his anſwer was, <hi>God forbid, I ſeek not revenge, I freely forgive him, and the reſt; only I deſire to be vindicated from
<pb facs="tcp:158496:4"/>their unjuſt aſperſions; eſpecially that,</hi> [that for ought they know I may be a Papiſt,] <hi>whereas I never ſpake word to any of them in my life.</hi> Which imputation, how ſlanderous it was, may eaſily be diſcovered by a paſſage in his greateſt extremity, wherein his diſcretion may (perhaps) be taxed by ſome, but his religion cannot be queſtioned by any. For, a very able Doctor of the Romiſh religion, being ſent unto him by a friend, he would not take what he had preſcribed, only becauſe he was a Papiſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the moſt remarkable paſſages in him during his ſickneſſe: The reſt of the time he ſpent in Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, and meditating upon his Word; eſpecially upon Chriſts ſufferings, and what a benefit thoſe have, that by faith could lay hold on him, and what vertue there was in the leaſt drop of his precious blood: interming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling here and there many devout prayers and ejaculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; which continued with him as long as his ſpeech; and after, as we could perceive by ſome imperfect expreſſions. At which time a friend of his exhorting him to apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to finiſh his courſe here, and prepare himſelf for the world to come; he ſpake in Latin <note n="*" place="margin">O dulcis Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator mundi, ſint tua ultima verba in Cruce, mea ultima verba in luce: In manus tuas Domine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendo ſpiritum meum. El quae ore meo ſari non poſſint, ab ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo &amp; corde ſint à te accepta.</note> to this effect (as I am told:) <hi>O ſweet Saviour of the world, let thy laſt words upon the Croſſe, be my laſt words in this world: Into thy hands Lord I commend my ſpirit: And what I cannot utter with my mouth, accept from my heart and ſoul.</hi> Which words being uttered diſtinctly, to the underſtanding of his friend, he fell again into his former Contemplations and Prayers; and ſo quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gave up his ſoul to God, the eight day of <hi>September,</hi> 1644. after he had lived two and fifty years, and lyeth bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the Pariſh Church of S. <hi>Leonards</hi> in Foſter-lane.</p>
            <p>Thus departed that bleſſed ſoul, whoſe loſſe I have great reaſon to bewaile, and many others in time will be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of. But my particular comfort is in his dying words, that <hi>God will be a Husband to the Widow:</hi> And that which may comfort others as well as me, is (what a reverend Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine wrote to a friend concerning his death) that <hi>our loſſe is gain to him, who could not live in a worſe age, nor dye in a better time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here again, I humbly beg the Readers pardon. For
<pb facs="tcp:158496:5"/>I cannot expect but to be cenſured, by ſome for writing thus much, and by others for writing no more. To both which, my excuſe is, my want of ability and judgment in matters of this nature. I was more averſe (indeed) from medling with the Petition, then any other thing I have touched upon; leſt (perhaps) it ſhould be thought to ſavour a little of revenge; but God is my witneſſe I had no ſuch intention. My only aim and ſcope was, to fulfill the deſires and commands of my dying husband: Who wiſhed all his friends to take notice, and make it known, that <hi>as he was trained up and lived in the true Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſo in that Religion he dyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>URSULA QUARLES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter from a Learned Divine upon the news of the death of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> QUARLES.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>My worthy Friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> Hawkins,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Poſtſcript.</note>
               <hi>I</hi> Received your Letter joyfully, but the news (therein contained) ſadly and heavily; It met me upon my return home from Sturbridge; and did work on my ſelf and wife, I pray God it way work kindly on us all. We have loſt a true friend; and were the loſſe only mine or yours, it were the leſſe, but thouſands have a loſſe in him; yea, the Generations which ſhall come after will lament it. But our loſſe is gain to him, (who could not live in a worſe age, nor die in a better time) let us endeavour like good Gameſters to make the beſt we may of this throw, caſt us by the band of Gods good Providence, that it may likewiſe prove gain to us; which will be, if in caſe we draw neerer unto him, and take off our hearts from all earthly hopes and comforts; uſing this world as if we uſed it not; ſo ſhall we rejoyce as if we rejoyced not in their uſing, and mourn as if we mourned not in the parting with them. —</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your aſſured friend NEHEMIAH ROGERS.</signed>
               <dateline>Essex. <date>Sept. 12. 1644.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:158496:5"/>
            <head>SOLOMONS Recantation, INTITULED ECCLESIASTES.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. I.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>1</hi> The Preacher ſheweth that all humane courſes are vain: <hi>4</hi> Becauſe the creatures are reſtleſſe in their courſes, <hi>9</hi> They bring forth nothing new, and all old things are forgotten, <hi>12</hi> And becauſe he hath found it ſo in the ſtudies of Wiſdome.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label> THus ſayes the beſt of Preachers and of Kings,</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Solomon</hi> the Sonne of <hi>David</hi> ſings.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> The greateſt happineſſe that earth can prize</l>
                  <l>Is all moſt vaine, and vaineſt vanities.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>3</label> What profit can accrue to man? what gaines</l>
                  <l>Can crown his actions, or reward his paines?</l>
                  <l>Beneath the Orbe of heavens ſurrounding Sunne,</l>
                  <l>What worth his labour hath his labour done?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> One Generation gives another way,</l>
                  <l>But earth abides in one perpetuall ſtay:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>5</label> The Prince of Light puts on his morning Crown,</l>
                  <l>And in the Evening layes his Glory down:</l>
                  <l>Where leaving Earth to take a ſhort repoſe,</l>
                  <l>He ſoon returnes, and riſes where he roſe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>6</label> The troubled Ayre provokes the Southern States,</l>
                  <l>And then it bluſters at the Borean Gates;</l>
                  <l>It whirles about in his uncertain Spheare,</l>
                  <l>And rides his unknown Circuit ev'ry where;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:158496:6"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>7</label> All Rivers to the Seas their Tribute yeild</l>
                  <l>And yet th'Hydropick Seas are never fill'd,</l>
                  <l>Their ſliding Streams purſue their paſſage home,</l>
                  <l>And drive their haſty Tides fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence they come.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>8</label> The world is all compos'd of Change; nor can</l>
                  <l>Her vanity be Character'd by Man:</l>
                  <l>The eye's not ſatisfi'd; and what we heare,</l>
                  <l>Fils not the Concave of th'inſatiate eare:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>9</label> The thing that heretofore hath been, we ſee</l>
                  <l>Is but the ſame that is, and is to bee:</l>
                  <l>And what is done, is what is to be done;</l>
                  <l>There's nothing that is new beneath the Sunne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>10</label> What Novelty can earth proclaim, and ſay,</l>
                  <l>It had no Precedent before this day?</l>
                  <l>No, no, there's nothing modern times can own,</l>
                  <l>The which precedent Ages have not known:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>11</label> The deeds of former days expire their date</l>
                  <l>In our collapſed Memories, and what</l>
                  <l>Times early Sunſhine hath not ripened yet,</l>
                  <l>Succeeding Generations ſhall forget.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>12</label> I <hi>Solomon,</hi> whoſe choice affections owne</l>
                  <l>The Churches ſervice dearer then my Throne,</l>
                  <l>Was choſen and anointed King, and now</l>
                  <l>Wear Iſraels Crown upon my ſtudious brow:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>13</label> I bent my heart, by wiſdome, to deſcry</l>
                  <l>What ere ſubſiſts beneath the ſpangled sky;</l>
                  <l>With ſuch hard travel hath our God thought good,</l>
                  <l>To exerciſe the ſoules of Fleſh and Blood.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>14</label> My thoughts have ponder'd all that hath been done</l>
                  <l>Betwixt the ſolid <hi>Center</hi> and the <hi>Sunne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, loe! the object of my <hi>Contemplation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is but meer <hi>Vanity,</hi> and ſoules <hi>Vexation.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>15</label> Not all this knowledge can reduce the ſtate</l>
                  <l>Of crooked nature to a perfect Straight;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:158496:6"/>Nor ſumme our Ignorances, which ſurmount</l>
                  <l>The language of <hi>Arithmeticks</hi> Account.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>16</label> I view'd my heart, and there found greater ſtore</l>
                  <l>Of wiſdome then all thoſe that liv'd before:</l>
                  <l>No knowledge could remain, no wiſdome lye</l>
                  <l>Cloſe from mine eare, nor clouded from mine eye.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>17</label> I gave my all-enquiring heart to know</l>
                  <l>Not wiſdome only, but ev'n folly too:</l>
                  <l>And I perceiv'd that all this Contemplation</l>
                  <l>Was vain, and nothing but the ſouls Vexation:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>18</label> For he that labours for much wiſdome, gaines</l>
                  <l>Grief in th'enjoyment; in purſuit but paines:</l>
                  <l>And who improves his knowledg, ſtrives to borrow</l>
                  <l>A fair advantage to encreaſe his ſorrow.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="soliloquy">
               <head>SOLILOQUIE I.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>How are the <hi>vain</hi> deſires of fleſh and blood</l>
                  <l>Befoold in that miſtaken <hi>Thing</hi> call'd Good!</l>
                  <l>How <hi>Travell</hi> ſeeks it! How unwearyed hearts</l>
                  <l>Make it the object both of <hi>Armes</hi> and <hi>Arts!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How many certain obvious ev'lls attend</l>
                  <l>The way to this uncertain Journies end!</l>
                  <l>We tyre the night in thought, the day in toyle,</l>
                  <l>Spare neither ſweat nor lucubrated Oyle,</l>
                  <l>To ſeek the thing we cannnot finde; or found,</l>
                  <l>We cannot hold; or held, we cannot ground</l>
                  <l>So firm, as to reſiſt the various ſwings</l>
                  <l>Of fickle <hi>Fortune,</hi> or the frowns of Kings.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Poor fruitleſſe Labours of deluded Man!</l>
                  <l>How vainly are yee ſpent? How ſhort a Span</l>
                  <l>Of ſeeming Pleaſure ſerves yee to requite</l>
                  <l>Long Leagues of Travell? For one drops delight</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:158496:7"/>Of ayry Froth, how are yee forc'd to borrow</l>
                  <l>Strong Gales of Hope to ſayle through ſeas of ſorrow?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why doe we thus afflict our lab'ring ſoules</l>
                  <l>With dregs of Wormwood, and carouſe full Bowles</l>
                  <l>Of boyling anguiſh? To what hopefull end</l>
                  <l>Droyle we our crazy bodies, and expend</l>
                  <l>Our ſorrow-waſted ſpirits, to acquire</l>
                  <l>A Good, not worth a breath of our deſire?</l>
                  <l>A Good, whoſe fulſome ſweetneſſe cloggs and cloyes</l>
                  <l>The ſoule, but neither laſts nor ſatisfies:</l>
                  <l>How poore an Object pleaſes! And how ſoone</l>
                  <l>That pleaſure finds an end! How quickly <hi>Noone!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How quickly <hi>Night!</hi> And what to day we prize</l>
                  <l>Above our ſoules, to morrow we deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>Beneath a <hi>Trifle:</hi> What in former <hi>Times</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We own'd as Vertue, now we taxe as <hi>Crimes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What is this <hi>World,</hi> but ev'n a great <hi>Exchange</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of dear bought pen'worths, all compos'd of <hi>Change?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where frothy <hi>Honor</hi> may be bought and ſold</l>
                  <l>With heart-corrupting, eye-beguiling Gold:</l>
                  <l>Where ſullen wealth, and friend-betraying treaſure</l>
                  <l>May paſſe in barter for repented <hi>Pleaſure:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where painted ſweetneſſe (though a grain too light)</l>
                  <l>Shall buy a Lords Eſtate for one poor night:</l>
                  <l>Where unſtain'd Beauties youth ſhall buy an old</l>
                  <l>Breath-tainted Churl, diſeas'd with Gouts and Gold:</l>
                  <l>Where Birthrights, Bleſsings, nay and ſoules to boot</l>
                  <l>(And yet not deem'd a pen'worth under foot)</l>
                  <l>Shall paſſe for fond delights: Where very <hi>Names</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Without an <hi>Aliàs,</hi> to lay after <hi>Claimes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To a poor Lordſhip) ſhall be ſwept away</l>
                  <l>For Clods of earth, and thoſe for one nights <hi>Play.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tell me, my puzzled ſoule, What wouldſt thou buy?</l>
                  <l>Goe in and cheapen: Let thy curious eye</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:158496:7"/>Make her own choice: They will preſent thy view</l>
                  <l>With num'rous Joyes: Buy ſomething that is new:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>9</label> Alas! <hi>there's nothing new beneath the skye.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Look further; further yet: Goe pleaſe thine eye,</l>
                  <l>Search, till the Object and thine eye agrees:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>8</label>
                     <hi>Thine eye's not ſatisfy'd with what it ſees.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Buy ſomething that will laſt; that will remain</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> To after dayes: <hi>All's momentary, all's vain.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I, but my ſoul, here's fairer Merchandiſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>16</label>
                     <hi>Wiſdome and Knowledge;</hi> That, to make thee wiſe;</l>
                  <l>This, to inſtruct thee: Come, thou needſt not fear</l>
                  <l>Too hard a bargain: Goe, and purchaſe there:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>18</label> Alas! <hi>much wiſdome makes thy grief but double;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Encreaſe of Knowledge brings increaſe of trouble.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, but my ſoule, the gracious eye of heaven</l>
                  <l>Hath ſmil'd upon thee. His full hand hath given</l>
                  <l>A large addition to thy thriv'n eſtate;</l>
                  <l>Thy Barns and Bags are fill'd; Thy ſervants waite</l>
                  <l>Vpon thy Buſineſſe, and their ſhoulders bear</l>
                  <l>Thy fruitfull Burdens; who, like Pilots, ſtear</l>
                  <l>Thy reeling Veſſell: Thou art richly'endow'd</l>
                  <l>With Knowledge, Wiſdome, Judgement, and allow'd</l>
                  <l>Some Graines to make thee weight; Me thinks, thy heart</l>
                  <l>So arm'd with ſtrong Reſolves ſhould never ſtart</l>
                  <l>At threatning ev'lls: Me thinks, thy daring eye</l>
                  <l>(If all the Cryſtall Rafters of the skye</l>
                  <l>Should make one Ruine, and that Ruine fall</l>
                  <l>About thine eares) ſhould be unmov'd at all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No, no, my ſoule, Tis neither Barne nor Purſe</l>
                  <l>Cramm'd up with Coyn or Corn, canbalk the Curſe</l>
                  <l>Entayld upon thy ſinne: Nor height of Blood,</l>
                  <l>Nor all that this miſtaken Earth cals Good:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>17</label> Not very <hi>Knowledge,</hi> no nor <hi>Wiſdome</hi> can</l>
                  <l>Exempt thee from the Common lot of Man.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:158496:8"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>16</label>
                     <hi>The wiſeſt Prince that ever bleſt a Nation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Found all things vain, and when enjoy'd Vexation.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. II.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>1</hi> The vanity of humane courſes in the works of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. <hi>12</hi> Though the wiſe be better then the foole, yet both have but one event. <hi>18</hi> The vanity of humane labour, in leaving it they know not to whom. <hi>24</hi> Nothing better then joy in our labour, but that is Gods gift.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label> SInce knowledge then affords my ſoul no reſt,</l>
                  <l>My roving thoughts try'd mirth, and were poſſeſt</l>
                  <l>Of all the pleaſures earth could lend; yet I</l>
                  <l>Found mirth and pleaſure all but vanity:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> I laugh'd at laughter as atoyiſh Antick;</l>
                  <l>And counted all my mirth no leſſe then frantick:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>3</label> My heart (but wiſely fooliſh) did encline</l>
                  <l>To coſtly fare, and frolick cups of wine,</l>
                  <l>That in theſe pleaſures I might find ſome good,</l>
                  <l>To crown the ſhort lif'd days of fleſh and blood:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> I built magnifick Palaces, did frame</l>
                  <l>Great buildings to the glory of my name:</l>
                  <l>I planted Vineyards, whoſe plump Cluſters might</l>
                  <l>Rejoyce my heart, and lend my ſoule delight:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>5</label> I made me fruitfull Orchards for my pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>And curious Gardens to refreſh my leiſure;</l>
                  <l>I ſtored them with trees, and theſe with Bowers,</l>
                  <l>And made a <hi>Paradiſe</hi> of fruits and flowers:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>6</label> I made me ſtanding pooles, to entertain</l>
                  <l>My breathleſſe gueſts and all their num'rous train:</l>
                  <l>I cut me Aquiducts, whoſe current flees</l>
                  <l>And waters all my wilderneſſe of trees:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:158496:8"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>7</label> Armies of ſervants doe attend my ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Both foreiners, and borne within my gate:</l>
                  <l>Herds I poſſeſt, and flocks above all them</l>
                  <l>That reign'd before me in Jeruſalem:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>8</label> Abundant ſilver, gold, and precious ſtones</l>
                  <l>By Kings preſented, my Exchequer ownes:</l>
                  <l>All ſorts of Muſick (earths delight) had I</l>
                  <l>To feed mine ear, Beauties to pleaſe mine eye:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>9</label> Such State, magnificence, and princely ſtore</l>
                  <l>Wondring Jerus'lem never ſaw before:</l>
                  <l>In all this pomp, my heart had not forgot</l>
                  <l>The lawfull uſe: My wiſdome fail'd me not:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>10</label> I gave mine eyes what ere mine eyes requir'd,</l>
                  <l>Deny'd my heart no mirth my heart deſir'd:</l>
                  <l>For my poor hearts delight was all my gains,</l>
                  <l>My pleaſure was the portion of my pains.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>11</label> At length I caſt my ſerious eye upon</l>
                  <l>My painfull works, and what my hands have done:</l>
                  <l>But loe, beneath the Sun no Contentation,</l>
                  <l>All, all was vanity, and ſoules vexation.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>12</label> With that I turn'd my weary thoughts agen</l>
                  <l>On wiſdome, and the fooliſhneſſe of men;</l>
                  <l>(Search they that pleaſe to ſearch, alas! there's none</l>
                  <l>Can ſearch the truth more ſtrict then <hi>Solomon</hi>)</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>13</label> When my impartiall Judgement did compare</l>
                  <l>Folly with wiſdome, this doth ev'n as farre</l>
                  <l>Excell the other, as Meridian light</l>
                  <l>Excels the ſhadows of the darkeſt night:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>14</label> The wiſe mans eyes are in his head; They ſtand</l>
                  <l>Like Watchmen in the Towre, to guard the land;</l>
                  <l>But fools haunt darkneſſe; yet my ſelf perceive</l>
                  <l>The ſelf-ſame lot both fools and wiſemen have.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>15</label> Ah! then (ſaid I) if equall fortune lies</l>
                  <l>For fools and me, what vantage to be wiſe?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:158496:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>What profit hath my wiſdome? Then thought I</l>
                  <l>The height of wiſdome hath her Vanity.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>16</label> The fooliſh Bauble and the learned Bayes</l>
                  <l>Are both forgotten in ſucceeding dayes:</l>
                  <l>Impartiall death ſhall cloſe the dying eyes</l>
                  <l>Both of the fool and alſo of the wiſe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>17</label> Therefore I hated life, for from th'events</l>
                  <l>Of humane actions flow my diſcontents:</l>
                  <l>Life ſpent in action, or in contemplation,</l>
                  <l>Is all but vanity, and ſouls Vexation.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>18</label> I hated all that e'r my hands had done</l>
                  <l>In ſeeking happineſſe beneath the Sunne;</l>
                  <l>For what I did I cannot call mine own,</l>
                  <l>Anothers hand muſt reap what mine hath ſown.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>19</label> Who knows if my ſucceſſor is to be</l>
                  <l>A wiſe man or a fool? Howe'r 'tis he</l>
                  <l>Muſt ſpend with eaſe, what I have earn'd with pain</l>
                  <l>And ſoules Vexation; This is alſo vain:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>20</label> For which, my ſoul (thus fool'd with vain purſuit</l>
                  <l>Of bloſſom'd happineſſe that bears no fruit)</l>
                  <l>Whiſper'd deſpair of all that I had done</l>
                  <l>To purchaſe perfect good beneath the Sunne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>21</label> Some men there be whoſe more elaborate gains</l>
                  <l>(The fruits of lawfull cares, and prudent pains)</l>
                  <l>Deſcend to thoſe that knew nor pains nor Art;</l>
                  <l>This is a vanity and afflicts the heart.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>22</label> For what reward hath man of all his droyle,</l>
                  <l>His ev'ning trouble, and his morning toyle,</l>
                  <l>His hearts vexation, and his griefs that run</l>
                  <l>Through all his labours underneath the Sun?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>23</label> His days are ſorrows; tedious griefs attend</l>
                  <l>His travail, hopeleſſe of a Journies end;</l>
                  <l>His reſtleſſe nights afford his cloſed eye</l>
                  <l>No ſlumbers: This is alſo vanity.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:158496:9"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>24</label> There's nothing ſweeter then to take repaſt</l>
                  <l>Of meats and drinks, and now and then, to caſt</l>
                  <l>Griefs burthen off, and gently looſe the rains</l>
                  <l>By intermingling pleaſures with our pains:</l>
                  <l>But this, I know, lies not in our command,</l>
                  <l>It is a bleſſing from th'Almighties hand:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>25</label> For who can eat? what mortall can apply</l>
                  <l>His heart to force a pleaſure more then I?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>26</label> Heav'n gives the juſt man wiſdome, knowledge, mirth;</l>
                  <l>To ſinners, travell; to heap earth to earth;</l>
                  <l>Wherewith t'enrich the righteous Generation;</l>
                  <l>This is his vanity, and ſoules Vexation.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="soliloquy">
               <head>SOLILOQUIE II.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BVt ſtay my Soul! Art thou reſolved, than,</l>
                  <l>T'abjure delight, and turn Capuccian?</l>
                  <l>Becauſe thy earth hath thus eclips'd the light</l>
                  <l>Of thy Contentment, wilt thou make it night?</l>
                  <l>Wert thou condemn'd to ſorrows? Wert thou born</l>
                  <l>To live in languiſhment, and die forlorn?</l>
                  <l>Abuſe not thy Creation: Thou wert made</l>
                  <l>Not thus to ſterve thy bloſſomes in the ſhade</l>
                  <l>Of barren melancholy; or to waſt</l>
                  <l>Thy penſive howres in the boyſterous blaſt</l>
                  <l>Of ſtormy diſcontent: <hi>Come, come, my ſoule,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label>
                     <hi>Hoyſt up thy Sailes to mirth:</hi> Let others houle</l>
                  <l>And whine: Let ſuch as always art at wars</l>
                  <l>With their own fortunes, curſe their ill-fac'd ſtars:</l>
                  <l>Paſſe thou thy frolique youth in Revels, ſports,</l>
                  <l>And freſh delights: frequent the purple Courts</l>
                  <l>Of proſperous <hi>Princes:</hi> Stue thy heart in mirth,</l>
                  <l>And cruſh the childe of ſorrow in her birth:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:158496:10"/>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> O but, my ſoule, <hi>what profit can accrew</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>From laviſh mirth?</hi> What pleaſure is't, to skrue</l>
                  <l>An Antick face and grimme? or to enforce</l>
                  <l>An empty laughter in a vain diſcourſe?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>3</label> Why then my ſoul, <hi>Goe winde the Plummets up</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of thy down ſpirits, with a chirping Cup:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Redeem thee from the gripes of Care, and rapes</l>
                  <l>Of Grief, and drench them in the blood of Grapes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, but perchance in that ſad heart of thine</l>
                  <l>There is a wound, craves rather Oyle then wine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If then thy cure prove worſe then thy diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>That Grief thou dar'ſt not cure, attempt to eaſe:</l>
                  <l>Forget thy ſorrows; or if rugged ſenſe</l>
                  <l>Will not be woo'd by language to diſpence</l>
                  <l>With her provoking foe, adviſe with Art:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſtubborn ſtreams thou canſt not ſtop, divert:</l>
                  <l>And like a pain-afflicted ſtripling, play</l>
                  <l>With ſome new Toy, to while thy grief away.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> Goe, raiſe <hi>great works,</hi> whoſe ſtructure may impart</l>
                  <l>The Maſters wiſdome, and the Builders Art:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Build houſes,</hi> whoſe magnificence may proclaime</l>
                  <l>Thy worth, as laſting Monuments of thy name.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>5</label>
                     <hi>Plant Orchards</hi> for thy Pleaſure: Deck thy Bowers</l>
                  <l>With dainty <hi>fruits,</hi> and delectable Flowers:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>6</label> Cut <hi>Waterworks:</hi> inſtruct the ſilver Tide</l>
                  <l>To wanton up and down: Teach her to ſlide</l>
                  <l>In ſoft Meanders, through the fluid veynes</l>
                  <l>Of the green breaſted ſtream-embroydred Plaines;</l>
                  <l>Raviſh thy ſoule with Muſick, and refreſh</l>
                  <l>The waſted ſpirits of thy unwieldy fleſh</l>
                  <l>With high-bred Raptures: Let harmonious Ayres</l>
                  <l>Compoſe the diſcords of thy droyling Cares:</l>
                  <l>Take pleaſure in thy pale-encloſed Grounds,</l>
                  <l>And let the Rhet'rick of thy deep-mouth'd Hounds</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:158496:10"/>perſwade thy head-ſtrong ſorrows ſo to fly</l>
                  <l>Before thy Heard, as they before the Cry:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Alas, Alas, my poor deluded ſoule,</l>
                  <l>Think'ſt thou to quench thy fire with oyle, or for to coole</l>
                  <l>Thy flame with Cordials? Can thy born diſeaſe</l>
                  <l>Expect a Cure from ſuch Receipts as theſe?</l>
                  <l>No no, thoſe Bellowes mount the blaze the higher,</l>
                  <l>Thou leap'ſt but from the Pan into the fire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>12</label> I, but my ſoule, me thinks a <hi>wiſe forecaſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Though not redreſſe the miſchiefes that are paſt)</l>
                  <l>May claim ſome kind of priv'ledge to prevent</l>
                  <l>The ev'lls that future Changes may preſent;</l>
                  <l>If not, what harm, what diſconvenience lies</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>13</label> In being foole? what <hi>vantage to be wiſe?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>15</label>
                     <hi>Both fool and wiſe muſt pay an equall ſhot</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>At Natures Table;</hi> have the ſelf-ſame lot.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why then, my ſoule, ſince ſorrow needs muſt haunt</l>
                  <l>Thy life, condemn'd to labour, ceaſe to daunt</l>
                  <l>Thy bold endeavours with the ſenſe of Care,</l>
                  <l>Cheare up thy whining heart, and <hi>take thy ſhare</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>24</label>
                     <hi>Of all thy labours, eat, and drink;</hi> and let</l>
                  <l>Thy ſenſe enjoy the wages of thy Sweat:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tis all thy Portion:</hi> Take what may be had;</l>
                  <l>Bad is the beſt; Then make the beſt of bad:</l>
                  <l>Sweeten thy pains; Mixe pleaſure with thy ſorrow;</l>
                  <l>Who knows to day what ſhall betide to morrow?</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:158496:11"/>
               <head>Cap. III.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>1</hi> By the neceſſary change of times, vanity is added to humane travail, <hi>11</hi> There is an excellency in Gods workes: <hi>16</hi> But as for man, God ſhall judge his works there, and here he ſhall be like a beaſt.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>1</label> THe great Creator in his wiſe decree</l>
                  <l>Hath pitcht a Time when every Change ſhal be,</l>
                  <l>And through his watchfull providence hath given</l>
                  <l>A ſeaſon to each purpoſe under heaven;</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>2</label> There is a time appointed for our birth,</l>
                  <l>And there's a time for earth to turn to earth:</l>
                  <l>There is a time to plant; A time wherein</l>
                  <l>To pluck thoſe plants, thus planted, up again:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>3</label> There is a ſeaſon when to build; ev'n ſo,</l>
                  <l>There is a ſeaſon to demoliſh too:</l>
                  <l>There is a ſeaſon to inflict a wound,</l>
                  <l>And there's another ſeaſon to make ſound:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>4</label> There is a time for tears to drown thine eye;</l>
                  <l>A time to laugh and lay thy ſorrows by:</l>
                  <l>There is a time to mourn; A time to meet</l>
                  <l>The ſprightly Muſick with thy num'rous feet:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>5</label> There is a due appointed ſeaſon, either</l>
                  <l>To ſcatter ſtones, or gather ſtones together:</l>
                  <l>There is a time t'embrace, and there be ſpaces</l>
                  <l>Of time, appointed to refrain embraces:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>6</label> There is a time to gain, and there's ordain'd</l>
                  <l>An other time to loſe the thing we gain'd;</l>
                  <l>There is a time to recollect and lay</l>
                  <l>Thy treaſure up; a time to caſt away:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>7</label> There is a time appointed when to rend;</l>
                  <l>And there's a time appointed when to mend:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:158496:11"/>A time for ſilence, and a time to break</l>
                  <l>Reſerved ſilence; there's a time to ſpeak:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>8</label> A time to love, and there's a time t'abate</l>
                  <l>Our warm affections; there's a time to hate:</l>
                  <l>A time of war, and there's a time to ceaſe</l>
                  <l>The Bloody Battell: There's a time for Peace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>9</label> If heavens decree thus bound the works of men,</l>
                  <l>What profit gains the fruitleſſe worker then?</l>
                  <l>What boots our Travell, or thoſe works of ours,</l>
                  <l>If all our plots depend on heav'nly pow'rs?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>10</label> Nor are our actions, or their ſecret ends</l>
                  <l>Govern'd by chance; nor doe our works depend</l>
                  <l>On hoodwink'd <hi>Fortune;</hi> no, pleas'd heaven thinks good</l>
                  <l>To exerciſe the ſouls of fleſh and blood:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>11</label> What ere he did, is fair, and timely done,</l>
                  <l>He gave the world for man to muſe upon:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe eye, with admiration may diſcover</l>
                  <l>The motion, not the progreſſe of the Mover.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>12</label> I know, that from the works of fleſh and blood</l>
                  <l>As they are mans, there can ariſe no good;</l>
                  <l>Unleſſe perchance to qualify with oyle</l>
                  <l>The ſoule-afflicting vin'gre of his toyle;</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>13</label> Or if it happen that his ſoul may eat</l>
                  <l>And drink, and reap the harveſt of his ſweat</l>
                  <l>To ſweeten ſorrows, may we underſtand</l>
                  <l>It is a gift from the Almighties hand:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>14</label> I know that heavens <hi>Decree</hi> is ſeal'd, and free</l>
                  <l>From alteration, a moſt firme <hi>Decree:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſo ordain'd, that the preſumptuous Race</l>
                  <l>Of man may fear the Majeſty of his face:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>15</label> The thing that is, hath been; and what of old</l>
                  <l>Hath been, ſucceeding ages ſhall behold:</l>
                  <l>The great Diſpoſer keeps the ſelf-ſame track</l>
                  <l>And calls his timely revolutions back.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:158496:12"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>16</label> I view'd the Chair of Judgement, where I ſaw</l>
                  <l>In ſtead of Righteouſneſſe, perverted Law:</l>
                  <l>I view'd the Courts of Equity, and ſpy'd</l>
                  <l>Corruption there, and Juſtice warp'd aſide.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>17</label> O then (thought I) the Judge of heav'n ſhall do</l>
                  <l>Right to the wicked, and the righteous too.</l>
                  <l>For there's a time true Juſtice ſhall proceed</l>
                  <l>On ev'ry Purpoſe, upon every Deed.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>18</label> Then puzzel'd in my thoughts, I thus advis'd,</l>
                  <l>Heav'n ſuffers mortals to be exercis'd</l>
                  <l>In their own miſeries, that they may ſee</l>
                  <l>They'r not more happy then the ſenſuals bee.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>19</label> To man and beaſt the ſelf-ſame lots befall;</l>
                  <l>Man dies; ſo dies the Beaſt: alas they all</l>
                  <l>Enjoy one breath; what Royalties remain</l>
                  <l>To Man above a Beaſt? For both are vain;</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>20</label> Both travell to the ſelf-ſame place; Both tend</l>
                  <l>Their paces to the ſelf-ſame Journies end:</l>
                  <l>The ſubſtance of their fleſh is both the ſame,</l>
                  <l>But duſt, to duſt both turn from whence they came.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>21</label> What curious Inquiſitor doth know</l>
                  <l>The place whereto aſcending ſoules doe goe?</l>
                  <l>Or can renown'd Philoſophy declare</l>
                  <l>Whither the dying ſpirits of beaſts repair?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>22</label> This rightly weigh'd, it ſeems the better choyce</l>
                  <l>For man to ſuck his labours, and rejoyce;</l>
                  <l>'Tis all the Portion he is like to have:</l>
                  <l>Who knows the entertainments of the Grave?</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="soliloquy">
               <head>SOLILOQUIE III.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>COme now my Soule; thou haſt with toylſome paines</l>
                  <l>Outworn the day; and, with thy dear-bought gains,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:158496:12"/>Thou haſt refreſht thy ſpirits; and, at length,</l>
                  <l>With luſty diet, haſt redeem'd thy ſtrength;</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt forgot thy labours; and thy Reſt</l>
                  <l>Hath crown'd Contentment in thy peacefull breſt:</l>
                  <l>Art thou now pleas'd? What can thy heart require,</l>
                  <l>More then thou haſt, to fill thy vaſt deſire?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>True; if my bubble life could get a Leaſe</l>
                  <l>Of this ſmall Reſt, nay, if the preſent Peace</l>
                  <l>Were but ſecur'd from this ſucceeding ſorrow</l>
                  <l>Long ſince deſign'd to the next neighb'ring morrow,</l>
                  <l>It were ſome happineſſe, and would preſent</l>
                  <l>A large proportion of a ſhort Content:</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Change</hi> (the Moth of tranſitory things</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label> That's never worſe then when the ſeaſon brings</l>
                  <l>A flaſh of Good) doth all things ſo unframe</l>
                  <l>That earths content doth ſcarce deſerve the name</l>
                  <l>Of common happineſſe; which like the winde,</l>
                  <l>Varies, ſtill meeting with a various minde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vnconſtant earth! what can thy treaſure ſhow,</l>
                  <l>That is not, like thy ſelf, unconſtant too?</l>
                  <l>How full of Change! How full of Alteration!</l>
                  <l>Nay, fixt in nothing but thy meer foundation.</l>
                  <l>And like thy ſelf, our naturall parent, wee</l>
                  <l>Conſtant in nothing but in loving thee!</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> One while we plunge in <hi>teares;</hi> and by and by,</l>
                  <l>We rage in <hi>laughter,</hi> yet not knowing why:</l>
                  <l>To day, the zeal of our affection's ſuch</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>8</label> We burn in <hi>love;</hi> tomorrow, <hi>hate</hi> as much:</l>
                  <l>Sometimes, we fear not when our ev'lls appear;</l>
                  <l>Sometimes, affrighted at no Cauſe of fear:</l>
                  <l>One while we ſhould and will not, will and ſhould not;</l>
                  <l>Nay, at the ſelfe-ſame moment, would and would not.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> Today we <hi>feaſt,</hi> and quaffe in frolique Bowles;</l>
                  <l>To morrow <hi>faſt,</hi> and pinch our guilty Soules:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:158496:13"/>Row, <hi>Muſick;</hi> now a <hi>Knell</hi> ſalutes our ears;</l>
                  <l>At noon we ſwim in wine; at night, in tears.</l>
                  <l>Ore night our vowes are made; our joy concluded:</l>
                  <l>To day the danger's paſt, and heav'n deluded:</l>
                  <l>The laſt ſix Months our fortune ſwell'd with ſtore,</l>
                  <l>And now they break; was never Job ſo poor:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>8</label> Time was, that <hi>peace</hi> enricht our joyfull Land;</l>
                  <l>Time is, our martiall drum beats <hi>warre</hi> at hand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vnconſtant earth! O, is it not enough</l>
                  <l>Thy days are ev'll at beſt; and but a puffe</l>
                  <l>At longeſt? At the fruitfulleſt but vain?</l>
                  <l>But ſad, at merryest; and at ſweeteſt, pain?</l>
                  <l>Is not all this enough? enough to make</l>
                  <l>The miſerable childe of man forſake</l>
                  <l>The falſe protection of thy magick eye,</l>
                  <l>Without th'addition of inconſtancy?</l>
                  <l>Is't not enough that we poor Farmers pay</l>
                  <l>Quit-rent to Nature at the very day,</l>
                  <l>And at our dying howre bequeath to thee</l>
                  <l>Our whole ſubſiſtence for a Legacie?</l>
                  <l>But thou muſt leave our frailties as a prey</l>
                  <l>To time-born Change, that will permit no ſtay</l>
                  <l>In one eſtate, nor give us leave to lye</l>
                  <l>Sad Patients in a quiet miſery!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O but my ſoule, why doſt thou thus contend</l>
                  <l>With thy Creators pleaſure? Ceaſe to ſpend</l>
                  <l>This needleſſe breath: Shall thy diſorder'd will</l>
                  <l>Confront his <hi>Providence?</hi> or call that ill,</l>
                  <l>Which he thinks good? Tell me, my ſoule, ſhall hee,</l>
                  <l>That gave thee being, be preſcrib'd by thee?</l>
                  <l>Hee made thee for his glory; not to ſpend</l>
                  <l>Thy days in ſlaviſh labour; nor to end</l>
                  <l>Thy painfull travell in the ſhades of death:</l>
                  <l>But thou haſt tainted that immortall breath,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:158496:13"/>Which qualifi'd thy life, and made thee free</l>
                  <l>Of heav'n and earth, and a joynt Patentee</l>
                  <l>With ſmooth-fac'd Cherubims; And too too proud</l>
                  <l>Of thy ſhort honor, warpt thy thoughts, and bow'd</l>
                  <l>Thy ſtraight deſiers to unknowne delight,</l>
                  <l>And wrapt thy glory in the clouds of night:</l>
                  <l>Loſt thy freewill to good, didſt overthrow</l>
                  <l>Thy perfect knowledge with deſire to know;</l>
                  <l>Bereft of wiſdome labr'ing to be wiſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>19</label> Now <hi>peer'd with beaſts,</hi> that only works and dyes.</l>
                  <l>Both, borne to ſorrow, breathe the ſelfe ſame breath;</l>
                  <l>Live both alike, both dye the ſelfe ſame death:</l>
                  <l>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce then, my ſoule, thy hopes may not aſpire</l>
                  <l>To what thou wouldſt, ſuit thy ſuppreſt deſire</l>
                  <l>To what thou mayſt: and let thy wiſdome play</l>
                  <l>Bad Cards with beſt advantage: what the day</l>
                  <l>Brings in by Travell, let the frolique night</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>22</label> Conſume in <hi>Mirth,</hi> and ſpend in full <hi>Delight:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Take thou to day, let others take to morrow;</l>
                  <l>He earnes the Solace, that endures the ſorrow.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. IV.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>1</hi> Vanitie is increaſed unto men by oppreſsion, <hi>4.</hi> By en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, <hi>5.</hi> By idleneſſe, <hi>7.</hi> By covetouſneſſe, <hi>9.</hi> By ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarineſſe, <hi>13.</hi> By wilfulneſſe.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label> MY ſoule return'd and fixt her thoughts upon</l>
                  <l>The hard oppreſſions made beneath the Sunne,</l>
                  <l>And, loe, the teares of captives in diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Cry'd loud for Comfort, yet were comfortleſſe;</l>
                  <l>Great was th'oppreſſors power, yet the griefe</l>
                  <l>Of the oppreſt was void of all reliefe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:158496:14"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> O, then, I counted their condition bleſt,</l>
                  <l>Whom death had lull'd in everlaſting reſt;</l>
                  <l>Yea, farre more bleſt then thoſe that live, to ſtand</l>
                  <l>Afflicted patients at th'oppreſſors hand.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>3</label> Nay, farre then both are they more bleſſed, whom</l>
                  <l>Conception never hanſell'd in the womb;</l>
                  <l>Or thoſe Abortives, whom untimely birth</l>
                  <l>Excus'd from all the ſorrowes of the earth.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> Imus'd againe, and found when paines had crackt</l>
                  <l>The harder ſhell to ſome Heroick act,</l>
                  <l>Pale envy ſtrikes the kernell with taxation;</l>
                  <l>O, this is vanity, and ſoules vexation.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>5</label> The ſluggiſh fool that ſolitary ſtands,</l>
                  <l>With yauning lips, and boſome-folded hands,</l>
                  <l>Conſumes his empty dayes, at laſt, is fed</l>
                  <l>With his own fleſh, that would not move for bread:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>6</label> His idle tongue thus pleading for his ſloth,</l>
                  <l>Better one hand be fill'd with reſt, then both</l>
                  <l>Stretch'd forth in travell, to prepare full diet,</l>
                  <l>With hearts vexation, and the foules diſquiet.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>7</label> Thus pauſing Contenplation ſhew'd mine eye</l>
                  <l>A new proſpect of humane vanity;</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>8</label> There is a lonely man that hath none other</l>
                  <l>To foſter then himſelfe, nor child nor brother,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe droyling hands thinke nothing can ſupply</l>
                  <l>The greedy wants of his inſatiate eye;</l>
                  <l>He robs himſelfe, nor knows for whoſe reliefe;</l>
                  <l>This is a vanity and wounding griefe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>9</label> The ſingle ſtate of him that lives alone</l>
                  <l>Is double griefe; Two better is then One:</l>
                  <l>For two can ſhare the ſorrows that befall</l>
                  <l>To one; One's worſe then not to beat all;</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>10</label> If eithers drooping ſhoulders be betray'd</l>
                  <l>To a ſad burden, there's a mutuall ayd:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:158496:14"/>Woe to the man whom danger meets alone,</l>
                  <l>For there's no arme to help him but his owne:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>11</label> When two divide the comforts of a Bed,</l>
                  <l>If one gaines kindly warmth, the other's ſped:</l>
                  <l>But warmth turnes back to him that lyes alone;</l>
                  <l>The ſteele will yeeld no ſparkes without the ſtone.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>12</label> If fury from a ſtronger arme aſſails,</l>
                  <l>One falls before the foe when two prevails:</l>
                  <l>But if a third put in a timely ſtroke,</l>
                  <l>The Cord that's threefold is not quickly broke.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>13</label> To be a poore wiſe child, is judg'd a thing</l>
                  <l>More honorable then to be a King</l>
                  <l>That's old and fooliſh, and whoſe diſpoſition</l>
                  <l>Checks at adviſe, and ſpumes at admonition.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>14</label> The low and lanke eſtates are often knowne</l>
                  <l>To clime from Priſons, to the princely Throne;</l>
                  <l>And glorious Monarchs have been ſeen to faile,</l>
                  <l>And change their glittering Glory for a Gaole.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>15</label> So have I ſeen the vulgar hearts grow cold</l>
                  <l>To with'ring Greatneſſe, whileſt their eyes behold</l>
                  <l>The blooming heyre, to whom Affections runne</l>
                  <l>Like morning eyes to greet the riſing Sunne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>16</label> Paſt Ages quench the fathers fading light</l>
                  <l>In the Sons hopes, and future dayes benight</l>
                  <l>The Son in his Succeeders expecation;</l>
                  <l>O, this is vanity and ſoules vexation.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="soliloquy">
               <head>SOLILOQUIE IV.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MY ſoule, to what a ſtrange diſguized <hi>Good</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Art thou bewitch! O how hath fleſh and <hi>Blood</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Betray'd thee to a happineſſe that brings</l>
                  <l>No comfort but from tranſitory Things!</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:158496:15"/>How is thy freedome curb'd! How art thou clogg'd</l>
                  <l>With dull mortality, beſlow'd, and bogg'd</l>
                  <l>In thine owne frailty! How art thou repos'd</l>
                  <l>In ſin-polluted duſt! embrac'd, enclos'd</l>
                  <l>In the foule armes of thy owne baſe Corruptions!</l>
                  <l>How is thy will diſturb'd with th'interruptions</l>
                  <l>Of croſſe deſires? deſires not knowing where</l>
                  <l>To finde a Center, rambling here and there;</l>
                  <l>Which, like their objects, alterable, rome</l>
                  <l>Like idle Vagrants without Paſſe, or home.</l>
                  <l>Review thy ſelfe my ſoule; Caſt up thy dayes,</l>
                  <l>They are but few; Thy life is but a blaze:</l>
                  <l>Goe take take an Inventory of thoſe Joyes</l>
                  <l>Which thy falſe Earth allowes: They are but Toyes,</l>
                  <l>To mock the frailty of thy flatter'd <hi>Senſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Attended with a thouſand diſcontents:</l>
                  <l>Hath Heaven enricht thy paynes with thriving drifts</l>
                  <l>Of mighty Gold? endow'd thy wind with gifts</l>
                  <l>Of ſacred Art? Or glorifi'd thy thy name</l>
                  <l>With honor, poſted on the wings of Fame?</l>
                  <l>What is there, then, that lyes in earths election</l>
                  <l>To rayſe thy happineſſe to more high perfection?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, but my ſoule, what great, what higher hand</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> Shall ſtop the mouth of <hi>Envy?</hi> Or command</l>
                  <l>Her ſnake-devouring fangs to keep the peace</l>
                  <l>Vpon thy worryed Name? To every Leaſe</l>
                  <l>Of earths beſt granted happineſſe, belongs</l>
                  <l>The ſharp Proviſo of malicious tongues:</l>
                  <l>They, they ſhall blaſt thy fortunes; leave a Tang</l>
                  <l>Vpon thy new-broach'd Honor: They ſhall hang</l>
                  <l>Like Burres, upon thy welfare, and deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>Like th' Eaſterne worm, the Gourd of all thy Joy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Or if thou chance to ſcape the whiſpering tongue</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label> Of ſecret Envy, Force, and bold-fac'd <hi>Wrong.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:158496:15"/>May hap to roar upon thy full-mouth'd Sailes,</l>
                  <l>And rude <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> with her Harpy nailes,</l>
                  <l>May gripe thy fair <hi>Proſperity,</hi> and grate</l>
                  <l>Vpon the vaſtneſſe of thy great eſtate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Or if thoſe forain dangers ſhould forbeare</l>
                  <l>To make aſſault; or made, prove leſſe ſevere;</l>
                  <l>From out thy very boſome may ariſe</l>
                  <l>Inteſtine Foes, to make thy peace, their prize:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>5</label> If that <hi>dull worme,</hi> that cloaths the moſſy land</l>
                  <l>With rags, but kiſſe thy <hi>boſome-folded hand,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It eats thy Treaſure with a ſecret Ruſt,</l>
                  <l>And layes thy bed-rid Honour in the Duſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Or if thy droyling hand ſhould once beſlave</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>8</label> Thy glorious freedome with a <hi>thirſt to have,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And take thee priſner to thy looſe deſires,</l>
                  <l>Thy happineſſe, even whilſt enjoy'd, expires.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Or if a liberall Content ſhould crown</l>
                  <l>Thy Gold with Reſt, and make thine own, thine own:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>9</label> Perchance, thou want'ſt a <hi>Partner,</hi> that may ſhare</l>
                  <l>In all thy fortunes: or (if ſped) an heyre,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe worth, and hopefull merits may revive</l>
                  <l>Thy honor'd Duſt, and keep thy name alive.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Or if the pleaſed hand of heaven ſubſcribe</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>13</label> To thoſe deſires, a <hi>ſelf-conceipt</hi> may bribe</l>
                  <l>Thy paſsion-guided Will to take up Arms</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt ſoveraign Reaſon, at whoſe bold Alarm's</l>
                  <l>Thy falſe affections may riſe up, and ſhake</l>
                  <l>Thy fancy-baffled <hi>Judgment,</hi> and ſo make</l>
                  <l>A Gap for miſchief, which may recommend</l>
                  <l>Thy reeling Fortunes to a ruinous End.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now tell me, O my ſoule, wherein can earth</l>
                  <l>Deſerve thy pains, or gratify thy birth,</l>
                  <l>In framing equall happineſſe; nay, in freeing</l>
                  <l>Thy partiall heart from unrepented Beeing?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:158496:16"/>O, is't not better, not to thirſt at all,</l>
                  <l>Then thirſt in vain, or quench thy thirſt with Gall?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>3</label> Are not the Cloyſters of the <hi>Barren wombe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Far more deſiderable, then to come</l>
                  <l>Into the wilde, into the common Hall</l>
                  <l>Of troubled <hi>Natures</hi> factious <hi>Court,</hi> where all</l>
                  <l>Move in their Orbs of Care, and ſeverall wayes,</l>
                  <l>Fulfill their <hi>Revolutions</hi> of ſad dayes?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> Are not the ſhady Bowres of <hi>death</hi> more ſweet</l>
                  <l>Then the bold Sunſhine, where we howrely meet</l>
                  <l>Freſh ev'lls, like Atomes, whoſe deluding breath</l>
                  <l>Tickles our fancies till we laugh to death?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our day of birth leads in our days of Trouble;</l>
                  <l>My ſoul prize not this earth; this Toy; this Bubble.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. V.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>1</hi> Vanities in divine ſervice, <hi>8</hi> in murmuring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt oppreſsion, <hi>9</hi> and in riches. <hi>18</hi> Joy in riches is the gift of God.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label> ATtend thy footſteps when thou draweſt near</l>
                  <l>The houſe of God; and be more apt to hear,</l>
                  <l>Then give the Sacrifice of fools, which know</l>
                  <l>Not in their ſacrifice whatev'll they doe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> Let not thy tongue be raſh; Commit no waſt</l>
                  <l>Of words before thy God by over haſt;</l>
                  <l>Since he from heav'n beholds thy actions here</l>
                  <l>All laviſh babling let thy lips forbeare:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>3</label> As dreams and reſt-diſturbing fancies flow</l>
                  <l>From floods of buſineſſe which by day we doe;</l>
                  <l>So multitude of words are daily ſprung</l>
                  <l>From th'idle fountain of a fooliſh tongue.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:158496:16"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>4</label> When thou haſt bound thee to thy God by vow,</l>
                  <l>Defer not payment, but perform it thou:</l>
                  <l>Diſcharge thy bonds, for heaven takes no delight</l>
                  <l>In fools, that violate the faith they plight;</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>5</label> Far ſafer 'tis thy vows were never made,</l>
                  <l>Then having promis'd payment, never pai'd.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>6</label> Let not thy lips enſnare thee; plead not thou</l>
                  <l>Before thy Angel, <hi>'Twas too raſh a vow:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O why ſhoutd'ſt thou provoke thy God, and dare</l>
                  <l>His curſe upon thy practiſe, and thy pray'r?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>7</label> Dreams oft are vain; and folly' is mixt among</l>
                  <l>The language of a multiloquious tongue;</l>
                  <l>But let the wiſdome of thy lips appear</l>
                  <l>Before thy God with reverentiall fear.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>8</label> Seeſt thou perverted Juſtice in the land,</l>
                  <l>And poor men grip'd beneath th'oppreſſours hand?</l>
                  <l>Stand not amaz'd; Th'Almighty views their way,</l>
                  <l>And there be pow'rs at hand more high then they.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>9</label> The fruitfull ſurface of the pregnant ſoyl,</l>
                  <l>Enrich'd by the laborious ploughmans toyl,</l>
                  <l>Brings forth to all; nay, very Kings doe build</l>
                  <l>Their whole ſubſiſtence from the fertil field:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>10</label>'Tis not full heaps of eye-rejoycing gold</l>
                  <l>Can feed, or ſcreen thy nakedneſſe from cold;</l>
                  <l>Nor can the piles of treaſur d wealth ſuſtain</l>
                  <l>Thy drooping ſpirits; This is alſo vain.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>11</label> As goods encreaſe, ev'n ſo their number, who</l>
                  <l>Muſt ſhare thy goods encreaſe, encreaſeth too:</l>
                  <l>What hath the owner more then they, but this,</l>
                  <l>What they conſume, his eyes behold as his?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>12</label> How ſweetly pleaſant is the ſleep of ſuch</l>
                  <l>As labour, eat they little, or eat much?</l>
                  <l>When as the wealth of idle Owners, keep</l>
                  <l>Their heart from quiet, and their eyes from ſleep:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:158496:17"/>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>13</label> There is an ev'll that happens now and then</l>
                  <l>Beneath the Sun, among the ſons of men.</l>
                  <l>Oft have I ſeen encreaſing riches grow</l>
                  <l>To be their great-made O wners overthrow;</l>
                  <l>And vex their ſouls with Care, and then repay</l>
                  <l>Unproſp'rous pains with grief, and melt away.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>14</label> His wealth is fled, and when he ſhould transfer it</l>
                  <l>Upon his heire, there's nothing to inherit.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>15</label> Look how he came into the world, the ſame</l>
                  <l>He ſhall goe out, as naked as he came;</l>
                  <l>Of what his lab'ring arm hath brought about,</l>
                  <l>His dying hand ſhall carry nothing out:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>16</label> This is a wounding Grief, that, as he came,</l>
                  <l>In ev'ry point, he ſhall return the ſame:</l>
                  <l>What profit can his ſoules affliction find,</l>
                  <l>That toyls for ayre, and travels but for wind?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>17</label> The pilgrimage of his laborious days,</l>
                  <l>Is ſordid and obſcure, and all his ways</l>
                  <l>Are blockt with troubles, and his ſouls diſquiet,</l>
                  <l>To gain his very life-ſuſtaining diet.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>18</label> I hold it therefore the moſt happy lot</l>
                  <l>To eat and drink, and reap what pains hath got,</l>
                  <l>To crown thoſe days which his Creator gave;</l>
                  <l>'Tis all the portion he is like to have:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>19</label> All ſuch to whom the bounteous hand of heav'n</l>
                  <l>Gives wealth, and licence to enjoy it giv'n,</l>
                  <l>To ſweeten labour, may they underſtands,</l>
                  <l>It is a favour from th' Almighties hand:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>20</label> Such, doubtleſſe, in their labour, ſhall forget</l>
                  <l>Their painfull ſorrows, and their toylſome ſweat;</l>
                  <l>For heav'n hath crown'd their fair deſires, and ſent</l>
                  <l>A peacefull conſcience, and a pleas'd content.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="soliloquy">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:158496:17"/>
               <head>SOLILOQUIE V.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BVt hark, my ſoul, the morning Bels invite</l>
                  <l>thy early paces to a new delight:</l>
                  <l>Away, away; the holy Saints-bell rings,</l>
                  <l>Put on thy robes, and oyle thy ſacred wings:</l>
                  <l>Call home thy heart, and bid thy Thoughts ſurceaſe</l>
                  <l>To be thy Thoughts; Go, bind them to the peace;</l>
                  <l>Take good ſecurity, or if ſuch fail,</l>
                  <l>Commit them to the all-commanding Jail</l>
                  <l>Of thy cram'd bags, there to lie cloſe and faſt,</l>
                  <l>Vntill thy heav'n-atoning vomes be past:</l>
                  <l>Confine thy rambling pleaſures to the truſt</l>
                  <l>of vacant howres: And let thy wiſdome thruſt</l>
                  <l>Indulgent <hi>Hagar,</hi> and her baſe-born child</l>
                  <l>From thy ſad Gates, Let them be both exil'd</l>
                  <l>From thy ſoft boſome; Let not <hi>Iſhmael</hi> ſhare</l>
                  <l>With holy <hi>Iſa'c; Iſa'c;</hi> muſt be heire:</l>
                  <l>Nor let thy ſorrow-melted heart bemone</l>
                  <l>Thy baniſht bondſlave, nor her thirſty ſonne:</l>
                  <l>Take thou no care for them; Heav'n will ſupply</l>
                  <l>Their craving thirſt with bottles from thine eye:</l>
                  <l>Leave all thy ſervill Fancies in the vaile,</l>
                  <l>Mount thou the ſacred Hill, and there, bewaile</l>
                  <l>Thy dying <hi>Iſa'c,</hi> whoſe free gift may be</l>
                  <l>A living pledge betwixt thy God and thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here maiſt thou feaſt thy ſoule, and fill thy breſt</l>
                  <l>With heavenly Raptures, and with holy Reſt.</l>
                  <l>Here ſhall thy Piety ſweeten all thy Rains,</l>
                  <l>And Grace ſhall here replieve what Grief diſtrains:</l>
                  <l>Here maiſt thou ſhrowd thee from thoſe ev'ls that wait</l>
                  <l>Vpon the frailty of thy frail eſtate.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:158496:18"/>Here may thy Griefs unboſome all their grones,</l>
                  <l>And find redreſſe from the high Throne of Thrones.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Haſt them, ô hie thee to that ſacred place;</l>
                  <l>Why ſtay'ſt thou? See, the widened Armes of Grace</l>
                  <l>Invite thy preſence, And with open breſt</l>
                  <l>Promiſe fair welcome to ſo fair a Gueſt!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O but my zeal-tranſported ſoul, take heed;</l>
                  <l>Too raſh a haſt brings oft too dear a <hi>Speed:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label>
                     <hi>Obſerve thy ſteps;</hi> Thy feet are apt to ſlide,</l>
                  <l>If thy miſguided paces ſwerve aſide;</l>
                  <l>Death waits at either hand, to make a prize</l>
                  <l>Of wavering footſteps, and miſwandring eyes:</l>
                  <l>Near the beſt bleſsings neighb'ring dangers dwell,</l>
                  <l>The very Suburbs of bleſt Heaven, is Hell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus when thy awfull preſence ſhall draw near</l>
                  <l>Theſe Hallalujous Courts, adviſe, and fear;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Put off thy ſhoes; 'Tis holy ground thou tread'ſt:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be not too bold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thou dy'ſt unleſſe thou dread'ſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now, may thy holy boldneſſe ſafely venture</l>
                  <l>To paſſe theſe delectable <hi>Port,</hi> and enter.</l>
                  <l>Now cloath thy heart with Reverence; Be fill'd</l>
                  <l>With ſecret Raptures; Let thy fancy build</l>
                  <l>No Caſtles here; Beware thou baniſh hence</l>
                  <l>The ſinfull objects of invited Senſe:</l>
                  <l>Make heav'ns command (and let thy zealous motion</l>
                  <l>Subſcribe to that) the cauſe of thy devotion;</l>
                  <l>Let heav'ns direction be thy form, and bend</l>
                  <l>Thy endfull heart to make heav'ns glory th'end:</l>
                  <l>Worſhip that's moulded in Traditious Schooles,</l>
                  <l>Is but the Senſuall <hi>Sacrifice of Fooles.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> Be wiſely <hi>carefull</hi> what thy <hi>lip</hi> impart;</l>
                  <l>Bring thy ſoft tongue acquainted with thy heart:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Be ſlow to ſpeak, and be as quick to hear;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Heaven loves a ſingle tongue, a double eare:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:158496:18"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> Make haſt to pay what thy <hi>vow'd Promiſe</hi> owes;</l>
                  <l>Deſtruction dwels in unperformed <hi>Vowes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus mayſt thou break the heart-corroding Fangs</l>
                  <l>Of griping Care, and ſcape the dying <hi>Pangs</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of living death: Here, here, thou mayſt controul</l>
                  <l>Earths power, and imparadiſe thy ſoul</l>
                  <l>In ſoft and ſacred Reſt, beyond th'extent</l>
                  <l>Of whining Grief, and murm'ring diſcontent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, but my ſoul, groſſe vanity, even dwels</l>
                  <l>In thy devotion, whoſe ranck offering ſmels</l>
                  <l>So ſtrong of earth, that very heavens deride</l>
                  <l>Our very Altars, and abhorre the <hi>Pride</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of our diſguis'd humility, which brings</l>
                  <l>Aſecret curſe upon our holyeſt things:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hence, hence, my ſoul, proceed thoſe boyſtrous waves</l>
                  <l>That plunge our frailties: This, ô this enſlaves</l>
                  <l>Our craven'd Spirits ſo, that we even faile</l>
                  <l>Or ſhrink before the Combat, and turn taile</l>
                  <l>To every ſlight affliction: this unlevells</l>
                  <l>Thy even-way'd Peace, with indigeſted evills:</l>
                  <l>This ſowers all thy ſweets, ſads all thy Reſt,</l>
                  <l>Nay diſpoſſeſſes thee, even whilſt poſſeſt</l>
                  <l>Of thy Imperious Treasure.—</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O then my ſoule, where ſhall thy wounds obtain</l>
                  <l>That ſoveraign balſome? who ſhall eaſe thy pain?</l>
                  <l>In what bleſt ear will thy complaints find place?</l>
                  <l>What holy Altar ſhall thy arms embrace?</l>
                  <l>If here be no protection for oppreſt</l>
                  <l>And lab'ring ſouls, where ſhall poor ſouls have Reſt?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Earths Joyes are vain, and they that ſhall commit</l>
                  <l>Truſt in vaine earth, are far more vain then it.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:158496:19"/>
               <head>Cap. VI.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>1</hi> The vanity of riches without uſe, <hi>3</hi> Of children, <hi>6</hi> and old age without riches. <hi>9</hi> The vanity of ſight and wandring deſires. <hi>11</hi> The concluſion of vanities.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label> THere is an Ev'll, which my obſerving eye</l>
                  <l>Hath taken notice of beneath the skye;</l>
                  <l>It is an ev'll frequents the troubled breſt</l>
                  <l>Of wretched man, and robs him of his reſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> To ſee where God hath multipli'd and giv'n</l>
                  <l>What wealth and honor earth can beg of heav'n,</l>
                  <l>And yet no pow'r to uſe it, but deſcends</l>
                  <l>To very ſtrangers: O, this Grief tranſcends:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>3</label> Who multiply their loynes and years, yet have</l>
                  <l>Souls unſuffic'd with good, and ſoil the grave</l>
                  <l>With blemiſht and diſhonor'd names, I ſay</l>
                  <l>Abortive births are better far then they:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> For he can hardly own a being, whom</l>
                  <l>Nature caſts forth from the untimely womb:</l>
                  <l>Darkneſſe infolds him in her ſecret ſhades</l>
                  <l>His name's forgotten, and his mem'ry fades.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>5</label> The worlds ſurveighing Lamp does not affright.</l>
                  <l>The pleaſing ſlumbers of his peacefull night:</l>
                  <l>There be no ears, no eyes, to hear, to ſee;</l>
                  <l>The living ſoul hath not ſuch reſt as he:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>6</label> Yea though he live a thouſand years twice told,</l>
                  <l>What worth his eyes, can his ſad eyes behold?</l>
                  <l>Doe they not both arrive, not both reſort</l>
                  <l>To the dull portals of the ſelf-ſame Port?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>7</label> The beſt reward of mans laborious ſweat</l>
                  <l>Is but a morſell of quotidian meat:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:158496:19"/>This may ſuffice his body,<note place="margin">Verſe</note> but the will</l>
                  <l>Of his inſatiate ſoule what hand can fill?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>8</label> What is it then the wiſemans labour gains</l>
                  <l>More then the painfull foole by all his pains?</l>
                  <l>What wants the poore man that by prudent labour</l>
                  <l>Knowes how to live, more then his wealthy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>9</label> Better enjoy a competence, and crave not</l>
                  <l>More wealth, then ſtil deſire the wealth we have not.</l>
                  <l>To wiſh, what if enjoy'd brings moleſtation,</l>
                  <l>Is but meere vanity, and ſoules vexation.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>10</label> The worldly confluence of treaſure can</l>
                  <l>Exempt no mortall from the lot of man.</l>
                  <l>Nor can his wealth inſtruct him to withſtands</l>
                  <l>The angry ſtrokes of the Almighties hand:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>11</label> Since the encreaſe of wealth procur'd by pain,</l>
                  <l>Preſerv'd with feare, with ſorrow loſt again,</l>
                  <l>Encreaſeth griefe in the poſſeſſors breſt,</l>
                  <l>What vantage then hath man to be poſſeſt?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>12</label> Who knows, what's good for man in this dull blaze</l>
                  <l>Of life, his ſwift, his ſhadow flying dayes?</l>
                  <l>Or who can tell, when his ſhort houre is run,</l>
                  <l>Th'event of all his toyle beneath the Sun?</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="soliloquy">
               <head>SOLILOQUIE VI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHat meant that great-creating Pow'r to frame</l>
                  <l>This ſpatious <hi>Vniverſe?</hi> Was not his name</l>
                  <l>Glorious enough without a Witneſſe? Why</l>
                  <l>Did that corrected Twilight of his eye</l>
                  <l>Vnmuſsle darkneſſe, and with morning light</l>
                  <l>Redeeme the day from new baptized night?</l>
                  <l>What meant that ſacred Rower to command</l>
                  <l>Divorce betwixt united Sea and Land?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:158496:20"/>Why wrapt heearth (as yet untouch with ſhowers)</l>
                  <l>In a greene Robe embroid'red all with flowers?</l>
                  <l>What meant the Beames of his refulgent eyes</l>
                  <l>To print their Image in the cryſtall skyes?</l>
                  <l>What princely gueſts with all their num'rous traine</l>
                  <l>Did he expect? was he to entertaine?</l>
                  <l>That his magnificent, his bounteous hand</l>
                  <l>Made ſuch Proviſion both by ſea and land?</l>
                  <l>What royall State's at hand? what Potentate:</l>
                  <l>On whom muſt all theſe Royall armies wait?</l>
                  <l>Who worthy of ſo great a preparation,</l>
                  <l>Is th'object of ſuch royall expectation?</l>
                  <l>What Prince is to be borne? What glorious birth</l>
                  <l>Is to be celebrated?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Groaning earth</l>
                  <l>Brought forth a lump not much above a ſpan,</l>
                  <l>A little naked, puling thing, cal'd <hi>Man.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Man,</hi> a poore ſhiftleſſe tranſitory thing,</l>
                  <l>Borne without ſword or ſhield, not having wing</l>
                  <l>To fly from threatning danger, not an arme</l>
                  <l>To grapple with thoſe num'rous ev'lls that ſwarme</l>
                  <l>About his newborne frailty, warpt aſide</l>
                  <l>From faire obedience to rebellious Pride.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Man,</hi> whoſe frame the great <hi>Three-One</hi> advis'd,</l>
                  <l>And with a ſtudied hand epitomiz'd</l>
                  <l>The large, voluminous, and perfect ſtory</l>
                  <l>Of all his workes;The Manuall of his Glory:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Man,</hi> in whoſe ſoule, the all <hi>Eternall</hi> drew</l>
                  <l>The Image of himſelfe, for earth to view</l>
                  <l>With feare and wonder, in whoſe ſov'raign eye</l>
                  <l>He breath'd the flames of dreadfull Majeſty,</l>
                  <l>Fill'd him with power, entruſted to his hand</l>
                  <l>Earths Empire, and the lower worlds command;</l>
                  <l>Crown'd him with glory, made him little lower</l>
                  <l>Then heav'n-bred Angels, that excell in power.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:158496:20"/>
                  <l>O but my ſoule, how is that hand aſham'd</l>
                  <l>Of his owne work! How is this frame unfram'd!</l>
                  <l>How is this <hi>Manuall</hi> blotted? Every word</l>
                  <l>How interlin'd? How is this Image blurr'd?</l>
                  <l>How are thoſe ſparkes of Majeſty, that were</l>
                  <l>So bright, now baffled with degen'rous feare?</l>
                  <l>How is that power that was bred and borne</l>
                  <l>The earth Commander, now become the ſcorne</l>
                  <l>of dunghill Paſsion, ſhipwrackt with the Guſt</l>
                  <l>of every fatuous and inferiour Luſt!</l>
                  <l>How is the Sunbright Honor of his Name</l>
                  <l>Eclipſt! How is his Glory cloath'd with ſhame!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Reflect upon thy ſelf, my ſoule: Enquire</l>
                  <l>Into the vaſtneſſe of thy vaine deſire:</l>
                  <l>What would'ſt thou have, which (being had) may fill</l>
                  <l>Th'unfathom'd Gulf of thy inſatiate <hi>will?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou level'ſt at a <hi>Good:</hi> Wherein conſiſts</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Good</hi> thou level'ſt at? To what ſtrange <hi>Liſts</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is her conceal'd <hi>Omnipotence</hi> confin'd?</l>
                  <l>Where is this will-commanding <hi>Saint</hi> enſhrin'd?</l>
                  <l>Is not her royall perſon gone to view</l>
                  <l>The Mines of <hi>Ophir,</hi> or the rich <hi>Peru?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or is ſhe gone to oyle the wings of <hi>Time</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With unctious pleaſures in ſome foraine Clime?</l>
                  <l>Or is ſhe mounted on the ſlippery <hi>Throne</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of ſtaggering <hi>Honor,</hi> there diſguis'd, unknowne?</l>
                  <l>Alas, my ſoule, if heaven ſhould ſuit thy ſtore</l>
                  <l>With thy deſire, thou wouldſt deſire yet more:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>2</label> Or if ſpring tides of <hi>Gold</hi> ſhould a degree</l>
                  <l>Tranſcend thy wiſh, perchance it would want thee:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>3</label> What if a num'rous <hi>Off-spring</hi> ſhould proclame</l>
                  <l>A perpetuity to th'laſting Name;</l>
                  <l>Or if the even-ſpun <hi>'Twine</hi> ſhould be extended</l>
                  <l>Till thou could'ſt number Nations all deſcended</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:158496:21"/>From thine owne loynes; yet, if the ſparing hand</l>
                  <l>of wayward Providence ſhould chance to brand</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>5</label> Thy dayes with poverty, th'<hi>abortive birth</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is more indebted to the gracious earth</l>
                  <l>Then thou, whoſe ſhadow-graſping hand even tires</l>
                  <l>Vpon the vanity of thy vaſt deſires:</l>
                  <l>Nay, if both heav'n and earth ſhould undertake</l>
                  <l>T' extract the beſt from all <hi>Mankinde</hi> to make</l>
                  <l>One perfect happy man, and thou wert <hi>Hee;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>finite</hi> fortunes ſtill would diſagree</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>7</label> With thy <hi>inſatiate ſoule:</hi> Some <hi>Qualmes</hi> of earth,</l>
                  <l>Hereditary to thy humane Birth,</l>
                  <l>Would print thy pamper'd ſoule with ſuch a freſh</l>
                  <l>And lively <hi>Character</hi> of feeble fleſh,</l>
                  <l>That all thy Joyes (doe Fortune what ſhee can)</l>
                  <l>May not exempt thee from the Lot of <hi>Man.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. VII.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>1</hi> Remedies againſt vanity, are a good name, <hi>2</hi> Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>7</hi> Patience, <hi>11</hi> Wiſdome, <hi>23</hi> The difficultie of wiſdome.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label> A good reputed Name is ſweeter farre</l>
                  <l>Then breaths of Aromatick Oyntments are:</l>
                  <l>And that ſad day when firſt we drew our breath</l>
                  <l>Is not ſo happy as the day of death.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> Better it is to be a fun'rall gueſt</l>
                  <l>Then finde the welcomes of a frolick feaſt:</l>
                  <l>There may'ſt thou view thy end, and take occaſion</l>
                  <l>T'enrich thy thoughts with fruitful contemplation.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>3</label> Better to cloud thy face with griefe, then ſhow</l>
                  <l>The laviſh wrinkles of a laughing brow;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:158496:21"/>For by the ſad demeanour of thine eyes</l>
                  <l>The heart's inſtructed, and becomes more wiſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> The wiſe mans ſober heart is always turning</l>
                  <l>His wary footſteps to the houſe of mourning;</l>
                  <l>But fools conſume, and revell out the night</l>
                  <l>In dalliance, and the day in looſe delight.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>5</label> The vertue of a wiſe mans fair reproof,</l>
                  <l>Brings greater benefit to a mans behoof,</l>
                  <l>Then all thoſe eare-bewitching ſweets that can</l>
                  <l>Belch from the language of a fooliſh Man.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>6</label> Look how the crackling thorns under the pot</l>
                  <l>Blaze for a ſeaſon, but continue not;</l>
                  <l>Ev'n ſo doe fooliſh flatt'ries entertain</l>
                  <l>Our ſouls with joy; but all that joy is vain.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>7</label> When wiſe men turn Oppreſſors, they have crackt</l>
                  <l>Their underſtandings in the very Act;</l>
                  <l>And the acceptance of a Bribe deſtroyes</l>
                  <l>The grounds of Judgement, and it blinds her eyes.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>8</label> In all attempts the onſet does not lend</l>
                  <l>So ſweet a ſatisfaction, as the end:</l>
                  <l>And he whoſe gentle ſpirit is endow'd</l>
                  <l>With meekneſſe, is far better then the proud.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>9</label> Let not thy hot-mouth'd ſpirit entertain</l>
                  <l>Too ſudden paſſion with too ſlack a rain;</l>
                  <l>For raſh and unadviſed anger reſts</l>
                  <l>Emboſom'd, and abides in fooliſh breſts.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>10</label> Let not thy murm'ring tongue deſire to know</l>
                  <l>Why former dayes were not ſo bad as now;</l>
                  <l>Where heav'n declares a Will, no wiſe mans eye</l>
                  <l>Should ſearch a Cauſe, or lips enquire a <hi>why.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>11</label> Wiſdome is profitable to advance</l>
                  <l>Mans welfare, joyned with inheritance;</l>
                  <l>By this conjunction profit doth ariſe</l>
                  <l>To thoſe that toile beneath the ſweltring skies.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:158496:22"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>12</label> Wiſdome's a Guard; and treaſure, a defence</l>
                  <l>To ſuperſede our wants, reliev'd from thence.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>13</label> Wiſdom's th'extract of knowledge, and convays</l>
                  <l>To the poſſeſſor everblaſting days.</l>
                  <l>O let thy thoughts enquire and underſtands.</l>
                  <l>The well-weigh'd works of the Almighties hand.</l>
                  <l>What he hath ſetled in a crooked ſtate,</l>
                  <l>No induſtry of man can make it ſtraight.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>14</label> In thy good day take pleaſure, and be wiſe;</l>
                  <l>In thy bad day have patience, and adviſe;</l>
                  <l>For heav'n gives both by turns, to let man ſee</l>
                  <l>How alterable earthly pleaſures bee.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>15</label> Much have I ſeen in this my ſhort-liv'd day;</l>
                  <l>Among the reſt, the juſt man ſnatcht away</l>
                  <l>In his juſt works, whilſt wicked find ſucceſſe,</l>
                  <l>And proſper in their long-liv'd wickedneſſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>16</label> Since then th'upright mans recompence is ſuch,</l>
                  <l>Be not too wiſe, nor righteous over much;</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould thy too much righteouſneſſe betray</l>
                  <l>Thy danger'd life, and make thy life a prey?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>17</label> Nor let the fleſh ſuggeſt thee, or adviſe</l>
                  <l>Thy thoughts to be too wicked, too unwiſe.</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould thy folly captivate thy breath,</l>
                  <l>And make thee priſner to untimely death?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>18</label> In all thy courſes therefore it is beſt</l>
                  <l>To lodge uprightneſſe in thy conſtant breſt.</l>
                  <l>For he that feareth the Almighty, ſhall</l>
                  <l>Outwear his ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll, or find no ev'll at all:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>19</label> Wiſdome affords more ſtrength, more fortifies</l>
                  <l>The undejected courage of the wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Then all the twiſted pow'r of thoſe that are</l>
                  <l>The Guides of Cities, or their men of warre.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>20</label> Yet is there none beneath the cryſtall skyes</l>
                  <l>So juſt in action, or in word ſo wiſe;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:158496:22"/>That doeth always good, or hath not bin</l>
                  <l>Sometimes polluted with the ſtains of ſin.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>21</label> At paſſions language ſtop thy gentle eare,</l>
                  <l>Leſt if thy ſervant curſe thee thou ſhouldſt hear.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>22</label> For oftentimes thy heart will let thee ſee</l>
                  <l>That others likewiſe have been curs'd by thee.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>23</label> This wiſdome by my travell I attain'd,</l>
                  <l>And in my thoughts conceiv'd that I had gain'd</l>
                  <l>No common height, but on a ſtrict reviſe</l>
                  <l>I found my wiſdome came far ſhort of wiſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>24</label> Objects far diſtant, ſecrets too profound</l>
                  <l>What eye can entertain what heart can ſound?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>25</label> I bent my ſtudious heart to ſearch and pry</l>
                  <l>Into the boſome of <hi>Philoſophy;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I gave my ſelf to underſtands the Art</l>
                  <l>Of folly, and the madneſſe of the heart:</l>
                  <l>I found the harlots ways more bitter are</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>26</label> Then death, whoſe arms are Ginnes, whoſe heart's a ſnare;</l>
                  <l>Whom heav'n doth favour ſhall decline her Gates,</l>
                  <l>But ſinners ſhall be taken by her baites.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>27</label> Loe, this I have obſerv'd, (the Preacher ſays)</l>
                  <l>By ſtrict enqueſt into their ſev'rall ways:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>28</label> Whereof my reſtleſſe, my laborious mind</l>
                  <l>Would make diſcov'ry, but deſpairs to find;</l>
                  <l>Among a thouſand men perchance that one</l>
                  <l>May be trac'd out, but among women, none.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>29</label> Loe here the fruits of all my diſquiſition</l>
                  <l>Only to know the devious condition</l>
                  <l>Of poor degen'rous man, whoſe firſt eſtate</l>
                  <l>Heav'n copied from himſelf, upright, and ſtraight.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="soliloquy">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:158496:23"/>
               <head>SOLILOQUIE VII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SInce then my Soul, the frail and falſe Eſtate</l>
                  <l>Of fading happineſſe cannot create</l>
                  <l>The leaſt contentment in thy various minde,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe fancy-guided motion cannot finde</l>
                  <l>The point of Reſt, but like the boyling waves</l>
                  <l>Toſt in the ſtorms of Earth, ſometimes outbraves</l>
                  <l>The threatning Firmament, then at a breath</l>
                  <l>Darts down, and daſhes at the dores of death;</l>
                  <l>Since waxen-winged <hi>Honour</hi> is not void</l>
                  <l>of danger, whether aim'd at, or enjoy'd;</l>
                  <l>Since heart-enchaunting <hi>Profit</hi> hath not fruit,</l>
                  <l>But care, both in fruition, and purſuit;</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>Pleaſure</hi> like a wanton itch doth breed</l>
                  <l>In the ranck fleſh, but ſcratcht untill it bleed;</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>laughter is but madneſſe,</hi> and high diet</l>
                  <l>Th'officious <hi>Pander</hi> of our owndiſquiet;</l>
                  <l>Since glorious <hi>Buildings,</hi> and magnifique <hi>Towers,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Fructiferous <hi>Orchards,</hi> odoriferous <hi>Bowers;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Full cluſterd <hi>Vineyards, Beauties,</hi> and the choice</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Muſick,</hi> both by Inſtrument and voice,</l>
                  <l>Can lend thy heart no full content, nor ſtill</l>
                  <l>The various clamours of th'inſatiate will;</l>
                  <l>Since humane wiſdome is but humane <hi>trouble,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And double <hi>knowledge</hi> makes our <hi>ſorrow</hi> double;</l>
                  <l>Since what we have, but lights our wiſh to more,</l>
                  <l>And in the height of plenty makes us poore;</l>
                  <l>And what we have not, too too apt to crave,</l>
                  <l>Ev'n diſpoſſeſſes us of what we have;</l>
                  <l>Nay, ſince the very act of our devotion</l>
                  <l>Can bring no Reſt, nor qualifie the motion</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:158496:23"/>Of our unbounded thoughts, to ſweeten out</l>
                  <l>This ſpan of frailty, plung'd, and orb'd about</l>
                  <l>With floods of Bitterneſſe: Since none of theſe,</l>
                  <l>Nor all can crowne our labours, nor appeaſe</l>
                  <l>Our raging hearts, O my deceived ſoule.</l>
                  <l>Where wilt thou purchaſe Peace? Who ſhall controule,</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall ſuppreſſe thoſe Paſsions that conteſt</l>
                  <l>Within the kingdome of thy troubled breſt?</l>
                  <l>Whither? to what ſtrange Region wilt thou fly</l>
                  <l>To finde content, and baulk that vanity</l>
                  <l>Which haunts this bubble earth, and makes thee ſtill</l>
                  <l>A ſlave to thy infatuated will?</l>
                  <l>Call home thy ſelfe: Inſpect thy ſelfe anew,</l>
                  <l>And take thy <hi>Birthright</hi> to afreſh review:</l>
                  <l>Thou art immortall; art divine by birth,</l>
                  <l>A ſpark of heav'n; Thou art not borne of earth;</l>
                  <l>Earth is the footſtoole of thy heavenly Throne;</l>
                  <l>Made for thy baſer parts to trample on.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Look not ſo low, my ſoule. There's nothing there</l>
                  <l>Fit for thy ſacred view; It is no Sphere</l>
                  <l>For thee to move in: No, let worms and beaſts</l>
                  <l>And ſalvage brutes trade there, and lay their Geſts</l>
                  <l>Of progreſſe, to ſurround with weary paces</l>
                  <l>The baſe Confines of thoſe inferiour Places.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, but my ſoule, th' Alliance of my fleſh</l>
                  <l>Claimes kindred there, takes pleaſure to refreſh</l>
                  <l>Her waſted body there: Earth is her mother,</l>
                  <l>The worme her ſiſter, and the beaſt her brother.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tis true, ſhe is thy ſpouſe, Heav'n ty'd the knot</l>
                  <l>For none to looſe but Heav'n: I know, her Lot</l>
                  <l>Is mortall, fraile, and being born of earth,</l>
                  <l>Corrupt and weares the Badges of her birth.</l>
                  <l>If ſhe tranſgreſſe, it's thou muſt beare the blame,</l>
                  <l>And all her deeds reflect upon thy name;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:158496:24"/>O then beware, and if ſhe needs muſt goe</l>
                  <l>To viſit earth, firſt, let her frailty know,</l>
                  <l>How apt ſhe is to fall, and ſhe how prone</l>
                  <l>To blurre, and ſtayne thy honor and her owne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>1</label>
                     <hi>A name unblemiſht with the ſinfull ſoyle</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of ſordid earth, is as a precious Oyle,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which like a ſoveraigne Antidote prevents</l>
                  <l>That plague of vanity which earth preſents.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then tell her, tell her, that her mother Earth</l>
                  <l>Muſt give her buriall, as ſhe gave her birth:</l>
                  <l>Tell her, ô tell her, Every gaſpe of breath</l>
                  <l>Are minuts moving to the howr of death:</l>
                  <l>And let her know, <hi>The houſe of mourning brings</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>2</label> More profit then the Palaces of Kings:</l>
                  <l>Tell her, Leſſe re all happineſſe doth dwell</l>
                  <l>In a <hi>full Banquet,</hi> then a <hi>paſſing Bell,</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>3</label> Arme her with <hi>patience</hi> apt to entertaine</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>8</label> Thy wiſe reproofs: but if her paſsion raigne,</l>
                  <l>Correct it wiſely: Teach her ſober eye</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>10</label> A willing <hi>ignorance</hi> in things too high.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If <hi>liberall earth</hi> ſhould chance to crowne her ſtore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>11</label> Let her <hi>wiſe modeſty</hi> receive no more</l>
                  <l>Then ſhe can manage; Pilots that are wiſe</l>
                  <l>Proportion out their Canvaſe to the skies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let not her knowledge with the Eagle fly,</l>
                  <l>Vnles her wiſdome have an Eagles eye.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>12</label>
                     <hi>Wiſdome</hi> digeſts what <hi>Knowledge</hi> did devoure,</l>
                  <l>Things ſweet in taſt, are indigeſted ſowre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>14</label> In <hi>proſp'rous</hi> fortunes let her joy be ſuch,</l>
                  <l>That in <hi>hard times</hi> ſhe may not grieve too much.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>25</label> Let her count <hi>wiſdome</hi> as her chiefeſt good,</l>
                  <l>And the price eaſie, whether ſweat or blood:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>29</label> And let the Percloſe of her thoughts be this,</l>
                  <l>To ſtudy what <hi>Man was,</hi> and what <hi>Man is.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:158496:24"/>
                  <l>So now my ſoule, thy well inſtructed fleſh</l>
                  <l>May viſit earth, and with her ſweets refreſh</l>
                  <l>Thy waſted ſpirit, ſecure from all thoſe ills</l>
                  <l>Which threaten ruine to diſtempered wills:</l>
                  <l>Now maiſt thou eat and drink, and make ſupplies</l>
                  <l>Tor after dayes, and cloſe thy peacefull eyes</l>
                  <l>In calme content, and ſcape thoſe hidden ſnares</l>
                  <l>That lurke in pleaſures, and encreaſe our cares.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He onely takes advantage of his Lot,</l>
                  <l>That uſes earth, as if he us'd it not.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. VIII.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>1</hi> Kings are greatly to he reſpected. <hi>6</hi> Divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is to be obſerved. <hi>12</hi> It is better with the godly in adverſity, then with the wicked in proſperity. <hi>16</hi> The worke of God is unſearchable.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>1</label> WHo's equall to the Wiſeman? who but he</l>
                  <l>Can judg of things, or what their natures be?</l>
                  <l>Wiſdome adornes the Cheek with lovely grace;</l>
                  <l>And plants courageous boldneſſe in the face.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>2</label> Let me adviſe the ſubjects heart to ſtands</l>
                  <l>Devoted alwaies to the Kings command:</l>
                  <l>For having ſworne Allegeance to him, both</l>
                  <l>Heav'n and thy Conſcience doe atteſt thy oath.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>3</label> Let not thy diſcontented haſt incite</l>
                  <l>Abrupt departure from his awfull ſight:</l>
                  <l>If thou haſt err'd, continue not in ill,</l>
                  <l>For Princes Acts are guided by their will:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>4</label> The potent Majeſty of a Princes word</l>
                  <l>Is backt and made authentick by the ſword:</l>
                  <l>What vent'rous tongue dare queſtion, or demand</l>
                  <l>The leaſt account from his illuſtrious hand?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:158496:25"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>5</label> Whoſe loyall breſts obſerve the laws of Kings,</l>
                  <l>Shall never know the griefe Rebellion brings:</l>
                  <l>The wiſemans heart knowes times, and judgement too,</l>
                  <l>Not onely when to ſpeake, but what to doe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>6</label> For there's to every purpoſe among men</l>
                  <l>A judgement how to doe, a ſeaſon when,</l>
                  <l>Which if miſtaken, or not underſtood,</l>
                  <l>Brings ſo much mis'ry upon fleſh and blood.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>7</label> For man is ignorant of what may fall,</l>
                  <l>And who is he can tell him when it ſhall?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>8</label> No man hath power to prolong his breath,</l>
                  <l>Or make him ſhot-free in the day of death:</l>
                  <l>There's no retreat in that ſad war, nor can</l>
                  <l>Mans wickedneſſe preſerve the wicked man.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>9</label> All this have I obſerved, and have given</l>
                  <l>My heart to note each Action under Heaven:</l>
                  <l>There was a time when the oppreſſors Arme,</l>
                  <l>Oppreſt his brother to th'oppreſſors harme.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>10</label> So have I ſeen grave Judges (but unjuſt)</l>
                  <l>That fat in judgement, honor'd to the duſt</l>
                  <l>Which hid their crimes; Theſe ſeemed to obtaine</l>
                  <l>Some happineſſe: This happineſſe is vaine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>11</label> Becauſe a preſent ſentence is not paſt</l>
                  <l>Vpon the wicked, their dull hearts at laſt</l>
                  <l>Grow quite obdure, reſolv'd, and fully bent,</l>
                  <l>Toact what ev'lls their greedy luſts preſent.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>12</label> Put caſe the ſinner multiply his Crime,</l>
                  <l>And his long dayes, ev'n ruſt the Sithe of Time:</l>
                  <l>Yet well I know they onely ſhall be bleſt,</l>
                  <l>That feare th'Almighty with a filial breſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>13</label> I, but the wicked ſhall not ſcape ſecure,</l>
                  <l>Though he live long, he ſhall not long endure;</l>
                  <l>But like a ſhadow ſhall his dayes appeare,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe he fear'd not whom he ought to feare.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:158496:25"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>14</label> There is a vanity reigns here below,</l>
                  <l>I ſee the wiſe man reap what ſinners ſow,</l>
                  <l>And ſinners ſhare when juſt men ſow the ſeed;</l>
                  <l>This Grief (ſaid I) all other Griefs exceed.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>15</label> Then prais'd I mirth, and held it the beſt choice</l>
                  <l>Beneath the ſun, to eat, and to rejoice:</l>
                  <l>For this is all the good, this all the gains</l>
                  <l>Is like to chear our days, and crown our pains.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>16</label> But when I ſet my buſie heart to know</l>
                  <l>Wiſdome, and heav'ns ſtrange working here; below:</l>
                  <l>(For day and night my ſtudies did deny</l>
                  <l>Sleep to mine eye-lids, ſlumbers to mine eye)</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>17</label> O then I found his works beneath the ſun</l>
                  <l>Paſt finding out; my fruitleſſe thoughts did run</l>
                  <l>This heav'nly maze, till they (at length) concluded,</l>
                  <l>Mans wit ſtoops here; here wiſdom ſtands deluded.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="soliloquy">
               <head>SOLILOQUIE VIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BVt ſtay, my ſoul! What language does appear?</l>
                  <l>Am I deceiv'd? Or did I ſeent to hear?</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Tenet</hi> ſhall I baulke? And which, embrace?</l>
                  <l>Hath <hi>Truth,</hi> like <hi>Janus,</hi> got a double face?</l>
                  <l>Did not that voice,<note place="margin">Cap. 1.18.</note> that voted <hi>Wiſdome vain</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But very now, <hi>now</hi> cry it up again?<note place="margin">Cap. 8.1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall what was late condemn'd as a diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>Now prove a Remedy? Such ſlips as theſe</l>
                  <l>Are brands of humane frailty, which belong</l>
                  <l>To us and ours; It well beſeems our tongue</l>
                  <l>To contradict and jangle: <hi>Error</hi>'s known</l>
                  <l>By many faces; Truth admits but one:</l>
                  <l>How haps it then, that <hi>wiſdome,</hi> whoſe encreaſe</l>
                  <l>Adds to our <hi>Grief,</hi> yet crowns our days with <hi>peace?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:158496:26"/>
                  <l>Be not deceiv'd, my ſoul; Let not one Name</l>
                  <l>Confound two Natures, and make two the ſame:</l>
                  <l>Shal Names give <hi>Natures?</hi> Dare thy tongue profeſſe</l>
                  <l>An equall priviledge to <hi>Curſe</hi> and <hi>Bleſſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For one Names ſake? No, my deluded ſoul,</l>
                  <l>Sooner may <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Darkneſſe, Fair</hi> and <hi>Foul,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sooner may <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evill;</hi> nay, <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hel</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May ſooner ſtartle from their <hi>Parallel,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And turn <hi>Joynt tenants</hi> in one perfect <hi>Line,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then theſe two Wiſdomes, <hi>Humane</hi> and <hi>Divine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That breeds a <hi>Tumor</hi> in the flatuous breſt;</l>
                  <l>This lays it: That brings trouble, and This, reſt:</l>
                  <l>That kindles fires, and thoſe fires encreaſe</l>
                  <l>To ſelf-contention; This concludes a Peace:</l>
                  <l>That duls the thoughts, ſuppreſt with low deſires;</l>
                  <l>This mounts thy ſoule with more heroick fires:</l>
                  <l>That cannot brook the tranſitory frown</l>
                  <l>Of Fortunes brow; This makes a Croſſe a Crown:</l>
                  <l>That fils thy hopes with froth, and blurs thy youth</l>
                  <l>With black-mouth'd <hi>Error;</hi> This directs to <hi>Truth:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That ſcorns advice, and like an own-ſelf <hi>Lover</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Befools thee; But this honors the <hi>Reprover:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That fears, and flees, or fals at every breath</l>
                  <l>Of diſcontent; This triumphs, even in death:</l>
                  <l>That breaks Relations, and for private ends,</l>
                  <l>Diſſolves Allegeance, and disbands true friends;</l>
                  <l>This loves ſociety, cals not <hi>Mine,</hi> but <hi>Ours,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yeilds due obedience to ſuperior <hi>Pow'rs:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That prickt by <hi>Paſſion</hi> ruſhes into crimes;</l>
                  <l>This backt with <hi>Reaſon</hi> counſels with the <hi>Times:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That gives the name of <hi>Power;</hi> This the thing:</l>
                  <l>That makes a <hi>Tyrant;</hi> This creates a King:</l>
                  <l>That lights thy <hi>Honor,</hi> fading like a blaze;</l>
                  <l>This crowns thy <hi>Name</hi> with everlaſting dayes:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:158496:26"/>That breeds a Serpent; this brings forth a Dove:</l>
                  <l>That works a ſervil fear; This filiall Love:</l>
                  <l>That deads thy ſpirit; This makes thee wiſely bold:</l>
                  <l>That ſcowres thy Braſs; But this refines thy Gold:</l>
                  <l>That fills thy Feaſt with Cares; with fears, thy Breaſt;</l>
                  <l>This makes thy morſell a perpetuall Feaſt:</l>
                  <l>That cools thy <hi>Palate,</hi> but inflames thy fire;</l>
                  <l>This ſlakes thy <hi>Thirſt,</hi> and ſatiates thy deſire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O then, my ſoul, correct that fleſh and blood</l>
                  <l>That blinds thee ſo; and, like a gloomy Cloud,</l>
                  <l>Thus interpoſes, and obſcurely flyes</l>
                  <l>Betwixt the ſacred object, and thine eyes:</l>
                  <l>Clear up, my ſoul, and like the eye of day,</l>
                  <l>Chaſtiſe that peccant darkneſſe, and diſplay</l>
                  <l>Thoſe miſts of earth, which like falſe Glaſſes ſhew</l>
                  <l>Fanatick figures, and preſent thy view</l>
                  <l>With ſpecious objects, precious in eſteem,</l>
                  <l>(Alas) but nothing leſſe, then what they ſeem.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then ſhall the wiſdome of that ſcarlet Whore</l>
                  <l>And all her bald-pate <hi>Panders,</hi> painted o're</l>
                  <l>With counter faited <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> appear</l>
                  <l>In her true colours, ſo that every ear</l>
                  <l>That hears her baſe Impoſtures, and the fame</l>
                  <l>of her lewd <hi>Piety,</hi> ſhall abhorre the <hi>Name</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of bloody <hi>Rome:</hi> Then ſhall the ſpotted Beaſt</l>
                  <l>Put off her golden <hi>Trappings;</hi> and undreſt</l>
                  <l>Of all her glory, be turn'd out to graze</l>
                  <l>In uncouth deſerts, and conſume her dayes</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Dragons, Tigers,</hi> and thoſe ſalvage things,</l>
                  <l>Now pamper'd with the bloud of Saints and Kings.</l>
                  <l>O then the crooked <hi>Paths</hi> of <hi>Error,</hi> fraud,</l>
                  <l>And Candle-light devotion, trim'd and ſtraw'd</l>
                  <l>With ſweet-lipt Roſes, ſhall appear as plain,</l>
                  <l>As tide-forſaken Rocks along the Main.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:158496:27"/>Then ſhall true wiſdome, like fair <hi>Sheba's</hi> Queen,</l>
                  <l>Begin her royall Progeſſe, and now ſeen</l>
                  <l>In perfect Beauty, ſhall erect her <hi>Throne</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In every breaſt, and every <hi>Solomon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall court her Glory, and intranc'd in pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>Shall ſmell her ſpices, and divide her treaſure.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. III.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>1</hi> Like things happen to good and bad. <hi>4</hi> There is a neceſsity of death unto men. <hi>7</hi> Comfort is all their portion in this life. <hi>11</hi> Gods providence ruleth over all. <hi>13</hi> Wiſdome is better then ſtrength.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label> ALL this I ponder'd, and at length I found</l>
                  <l>All actions, whether juſt or wiſe, are crown'd</l>
                  <l>By ſecret providence: And no man knows</l>
                  <l>Gods love or hate, by bleſſings or by blows.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> All haps alike to all; The ſame things doe</l>
                  <l>Befall the righteous and th'unrighteous too.</l>
                  <l>Th'unclean, and clean, have here the ſelf-ſame pay;</l>
                  <l>And he that prays, and he that doth not pray:</l>
                  <l>Alike befals to good and bad, and both</l>
                  <l>To him that ſwears, and him that fears an oath:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>3</label> It is a grief that grates beneath the Sun,</l>
                  <l>That like events betide to every one;</l>
                  <l>Which makes the deſp'rate hearts of men to rave</l>
                  <l>With miſchief, till they drop into the Grave.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> For the ambition of their hopes extend</l>
                  <l>But to this life, and with this life they end:</l>
                  <l>Better to be a living dog (they plead)</l>
                  <l>Then to be known a Lyon that is dead:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>5</label> For they that live know well that they ſhall die,</l>
                  <l>And therefore take their time; But they that lie</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:158496:27"/>Rak'd up in deaths cold Embers, they know not</l>
                  <l>Or good or ill: Their names are quite forgot:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>6</label> They have no friends to love, no foes to hate;</l>
                  <l>They know no vertue to ſpit venome at;</l>
                  <l>They fell no ſweat for gaines, nor doe they buy</l>
                  <l>Pleaſure with paines, or trade beneath the sky:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>7</label> Goe then, rejoyce, and eat: Let a full boul</l>
                  <l>Caſheire thy cares, and chear thy frolick ſoul;</l>
                  <l>What heaven hath lent thee with a liberal hand,</l>
                  <l>To ſerve, and chear thy frailty up, command.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>8</label> Indulge thy carefull fleſh with new ſupply,</l>
                  <l>And change of garments of the pureſt dy;</l>
                  <l>Refreſh thy limbs, annoy'd with ſweat and toyle,</l>
                  <l>With coſtly bathes, thy head with precious oyle.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>9</label> Delight thy ſelf in thy delicious wife</l>
                  <l>All the vain days of thy vain waſting life;</l>
                  <l>Of all the works thy painfull hand hath done,</l>
                  <l>This, this is all the price beneath the Sunne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>10</label> What ere thy hand endeavours, that may gain</l>
                  <l>Contentment, ſpare not either coſt or pain;</l>
                  <l>For there's no hand to work, no pow'r to have,</l>
                  <l>No wiſdome to contrive within the grave.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>11</label> I find the ſwift not always win the prize,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſtrength of arm the battell, nor the wiſe</l>
                  <l>Grow rich in fortunes, nor the men of skill</l>
                  <l>In favour; all as time and fortune will.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>12</label> Man knoweth not his time; As Fiſhes are</l>
                  <l>Snar'd in the net, Birds tangled in the ſnare;</l>
                  <l>So be the ſons of men ſurpriz'd with ſnares,</l>
                  <l>When miſchief fals upon them unawares.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>13</label> This wiſdome have I ſeen beneath the skye,</l>
                  <l>Which wiſely weigh'd, deſerves a wiſe mans eye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>14</label> There was a little City poorly mann'd</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt which a Potent King brought up a band</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:158496:28"/>Of Martiall ſtrength, beſieg'd it, and withall</l>
                  <l>Built mighty Bulwarks 'gainſt her ſlender wall;</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>15</label> In this half conquer'd City there was found</l>
                  <l>A poor wiſe man, whoſe wiſdome did confound</l>
                  <l>Both the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; all the works their ſtrength could plant;</l>
                  <l>Yet no reward reliev'd this poor mans want.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>16</label> O then (thought I) poor wiſdome will at length</l>
                  <l>Diſcover greater worth then golden ſtrength;</l>
                  <l>Yet is the poor mans wiſdome poorly priz'd,</l>
                  <l>His word's not heard, or being heard, deſpiſ'd:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>17</label> The whiſp'ring wiſe mans tongue prevaileth more,</l>
                  <l>Then when the lips of fooliſh Rulers roare:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>18</label> Prudent advice is more tranſcendent far,</l>
                  <l>Then ſtrength of Arm, or Inſtruments of war:</l>
                  <l>But raſh attempts of a miſguided hand</l>
                  <l>Defeat themſelves, and ruine all the land.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="soliloquy">
               <head>SOLILOQUIE IX.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BVt ah, my ſoul, what boots it to be wiſe?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>2</label> Or what <hi>Advantage?</hi> what great profit lies</l>
                  <l>In a fair Journy? to be well ſupply'd</l>
                  <l>With all Accoutrements, a knowing Guide,</l>
                  <l>A metled Steed, a ſweet and temperate sky,</l>
                  <l>Short miles, and way-beguiling Company;</l>
                  <l>When armed death ſtands ready to attend</l>
                  <l>Thy parting Stirrop at thy Journies end?</l>
                  <l>Thy wiſdome cannot ſave thee; ha's no power</l>
                  <l>To keep thee Shotfree, or to quit that hower.</l>
                  <l>Dull <hi>Nabals</hi> Howreglaſſe runs as ſlow a pace</l>
                  <l>As active <hi>Solomons:</hi> An equally ſpace</l>
                  <l>Divides their minuts; Deaths impartiall hand</l>
                  <l>Wounds all alike, and death will give no ſand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:158496:28"/>
                  <l>What then my ſoul? If wiſdome ſhould entaile</l>
                  <l>Our happineſſe on this life, or fill our Saile</l>
                  <l>In this wilde <hi>Ocean</hi> with perpetuall breath,</l>
                  <l>When ſhould we find a <hi>Hav'n:</hi> If partiall death</l>
                  <l>Should favour wiſdome, and not exerciſe</l>
                  <l>Her office there, 'twere miſery to be wiſe:</l>
                  <l>The prudent <hi>Pilot</hi> whoſe marinall skill</l>
                  <l>Makes the proud windes obedient to his will,</l>
                  <l>And ploughs the Billows with leſſe fear then wrong,</l>
                  <l>Takes no delight to make his voyage long;</l>
                  <l>But with his wiſe endeavours ſeeks to guide</l>
                  <l>His ſlender <hi>Pinnace,</hi> and to curb the pride</l>
                  <l>Of the rebellious waves, and doth addreſſe</l>
                  <l>His care to crown his voyage with ſucceſſe:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our life's the voyage, and this world the Ocean,</l>
                  <l>Our cares are waves toſt in perpetuall motion;</l>
                  <l>Our thoughts are buſie windes, that often blow</l>
                  <l>Too ſtrong a Gale, and toſſes to and fro</l>
                  <l>Our crazy Veſſels: Every ſoul does bear</l>
                  <l>The office of a <hi>Pilot,</hi> now to ſtear,</l>
                  <l>Now to adviſe; and ſtill to lay commands</l>
                  <l>Vpon th' Affection-Saylors, whoſe rude hands</l>
                  <l>Are always active, ready to fulfill</l>
                  <l>The wiſe directions of the <hi>Pilots</hi> will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It matters not, my ſoul, how long or ſhort</l>
                  <l>Thy voyage be, if ſafe; they gain the Port</l>
                  <l>With beſt advantage, that in peace arrive</l>
                  <l>With Ribs unſhook, and all their men alive.</l>
                  <l>It lies not in the skilfull <hi>Pilots</hi> power</l>
                  <l>T avoid tempeſtuous Seas, but to endure;</l>
                  <l>'Tis wiſdome to endure, as well as doe;</l>
                  <l>Who bravely ſuffers, is victorious too.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then chear, my ſoul; Let not the frowns of earth</l>
                  <l>Diſturb thy peace, or interrupt thy mirth:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:158496:29"/>Let not that rude, that <hi>Apogean</hi> ſtorm</l>
                  <l>Of fleſh and blood diſmay thee, or deform</l>
                  <l>The beauty of thy thoughts, or caſt thy minde</l>
                  <l>Into a baſe deſpondence: Let the winde</l>
                  <l>Blow where it pleaſe, a well-prepared breſt</l>
                  <l>Will give thee ſhelter, and afford thee reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When worldly croſſes tempt thee, underſtand</l>
                  <l>Heav'n tryes thy temper then; If then thou ſtand</l>
                  <l>Vpright in Court, and of unſhaken mind,</l>
                  <l>The Teſt approves thee, and thou art refin'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then chear, my ſoul; Let not the rubs of earth</l>
                  <l>Diſturb thy peace, or interrupt thy mirth;</l>
                  <l>If heav'n hath crown'd thy labours with ſucceſſe,</l>
                  <l>Enjoy it freely; <hi>Eat and drink,</hi> and bleſſe</l>
                  <l>The gracious Giver; Let thy ſoul rejoyce</l>
                  <l>And take a chearfull pleaſure in the choice</l>
                  <l>Of all delights; and what his bounty gave</l>
                  <l>With a free hand, fear not thou to receive</l>
                  <l>With a free heart: <hi>Refreſh thy fainting head</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>8</label>
                     <hi>With precious Oyles,</hi> and change thy carefull bread</l>
                  <l>To feaſts of Joy; Or if a Croſſe ſhould greet</l>
                  <l>Thy frolique ſoul, march bravely on, and meet</l>
                  <l>Adverſity half way; and with a heart</l>
                  <l>Too great for earth to wrong, ſhake hands and part:</l>
                  <l>Chear then my ſoul; Let not the rubs of earth</l>
                  <l>Diſturb thy peace, or interrupt thy mirth:</l>
                  <l>Goe, ſweeten up thy labours and thy life</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>9</label> With freſh delights: <hi>Rejoyce thee in the wife</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And partner of thy boſome; Let her breſt</l>
                  <l>Suffice thee as the Center of thy reſt:</l>
                  <l>Deny thy heart no pleaſure, that may lye</l>
                  <l>Within the lawfull limits of thine eye:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>10</label>
                     <hi>Take time while time ſhall ſerve;</hi> To morrow may</l>
                  <l>Be none of ours; Come, come, be wiſe to day;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:158496:29"/>And teach thy labours to beſtow their ſorrow</l>
                  <l>On thoſe that practiſe to be fooles to morrow.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP X.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>1</hi> obſervations of wiſdome and folly. <hi>16</hi> Of Riot, <hi>18</hi> Slothfulneſſe, <hi>19</hi> and money. <hi>20</hi> Mens thoughts of Kings ought to be reverenced.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>1</label> LOok how dead flies (though few in number) ſoil,</l>
                  <l>Corrupt and putrefy the pureſt Oil:</l>
                  <l>Ev'n ſo a little folly ſtains his fame</l>
                  <l>Whom fair Repute for Wiſdome lends a name.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>2</label> A wiſe mans heart is plac'd at his right hand,</l>
                  <l>His plots and counſels are of ſtrong command;</l>
                  <l>But hearts of fools are weak and raſh, bereft</l>
                  <l>Of ſage advice; their hearts are at their left.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>3</label> Nay, if their ſteps but meaſure out the way,</l>
                  <l>Their Garb, their Looks, their Language do betray</l>
                  <l>Their folly, read by whomſoere they meet;</l>
                  <l>Themſelves proclaime their ſelves in ev'ry ſtreet.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> If thy Superior happen to incenſe</l>
                  <l>His jealous wrath at thy ſuppos'd offence,</l>
                  <l>Doe thou thy part and yeild, for yeilding ſlakes</l>
                  <l>The raging flame, that great tranſgreſſion makes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>5</label> I ſee an ev'll beneath the Sun that ſprings</l>
                  <l>From error, reigning in the breaſts of Kings:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>6</label> Fools are made Stateſmen, and command at Court,</l>
                  <l>And men of parts are made the lower ſort.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>7</label> So have I ſeen proud ſervants mounted high</l>
                  <l>On Lordly Steeds, and Lords to lackey by.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>8</label> He that ſhall dig a pit, that ſhall prepare</l>
                  <l>A ſnare, ſhall be enſnar'd in his own ſnare.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:158496:30"/>And he that tramples down a hedge ſhall meet</l>
                  <l>A Serpent to ſalute his trampling feet.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>9</label> He that ſhall ſhake a ſtone-compacted wall,</l>
                  <l>Shall undergoe the danger of the fall:</l>
                  <l>Who undertakes to cleave the knotty Oak,</l>
                  <l>Shall be a painfull Partner in the ſtroak:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>10</label> But if th'unwhetted edge be blunt, the arm</l>
                  <l>Muſt give more ſtrength, and ſo receive more harm;</l>
                  <l>But if he challenge wiſdome for his guide,</l>
                  <l>Wiſdome will doe, what painfull ſtrength deni'd.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>11</label> The raſh reproving mouth of fools are arm'd</l>
                  <l>Like unenchaunted ſerpents, if not charm'd.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>12</label> The wiſe mans words are gracious where they goe,</l>
                  <l>But fooliſh language doth themſelves o'rethrow.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>13</label> Folly brings in the Prologue with his tongue,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Epilogue is Rage and open wrong.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>14</label> The fool abounds in tongue, there's none can know</l>
                  <l>What his words mean, or what he means to doe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>15</label> The tedious actions of a fool doth try</l>
                  <l>The patience of the weary ſtander by;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe his weakneſſe knows not how to lay</l>
                  <l>His actions poſture in a Civill way.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>16</label> Woe to the Land, whoſe Princes wiſdome ſways</l>
                  <l>The ſcepter in the nonage of her days;</l>
                  <l>And whoſe grave Rulers, that ſhould haunt the ſeat</l>
                  <l>Of ſacred Juſtice, riſe betime to eat.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>17</label> Bleſſed art thou ô Land, when as thy King</l>
                  <l>Derives his royall blood from th'ancient ſpring</l>
                  <l>Of Majeſty, and Rulers timely diet</l>
                  <l>Serves to maintain their ſtrength, and not their riot.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>18</label> By too much ſlothfulneſſe the building fals</l>
                  <l>Into decay, and ruine ſtrikes her wals,</l>
                  <l>And through the ſluggiſh poſture of his hand</l>
                  <l>The weather-beaten houſe forgets to ſtand:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:158496:30"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>19</label> Who eats and drinks and frolicks, uncontrol'd,</l>
                  <l>Maintaining riot with his wanton gold.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>20</label> Curſe not the King, nor them that bear the ſword,</l>
                  <l>No, not in thought, tho thought expreſs no word;</l>
                  <l>The fowls of heav'n ſhall vent ſuch hideous things,</l>
                  <l>And ſwift Report ſhall fly with ſecret wings.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="soliloquy">
               <head>SOLILOQUIE X.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BVt ah, my ſoul! How cloſely folly cleaves</l>
                  <l>To fleſh and blood! How mungrell nature weaves</l>
                  <l>Wiſdome and Folly in the ſelf-ſame Loome,</l>
                  <l>Like webbe and woof, whereby they both become</l>
                  <l>One perfect Webbe to cloathe our imperfections</l>
                  <l>With Linſy-woolſy, and our mixt affections</l>
                  <l>With fooliſh wiſdome! O how full of earth</l>
                  <l>Was our firſt <hi>Ore,</hi> which at our ſinfull birth</l>
                  <l>Was taken from the <hi>Womb;</hi> Now purifi'd</l>
                  <l>In ſacred Fires, and more then ſeven times tri'd</l>
                  <l>In ſharp afflictions furnace; yes how baſe</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Bullion</hi> is! not worthy of the Face</l>
                  <l>That makes us currant; O how apt and prone</l>
                  <l>Is fleſh and blood to fall, if let alone</l>
                  <l>But one poor Minute! Moſt in danger then</l>
                  <l>To be ſurpris'd and foyl'd with Folly, when</l>
                  <l>Our bold <hi>Preſumption</hi> tempts our thoughts to priſe</l>
                  <l>Our wiſdoms overmuch, and ſeem too wiſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label> How one raſh action; O <hi>how one dead Flie</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Embalm'd in thy ſweet <hi>Oyle</hi> does putrefie</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Box of Spikenard!</hi> How it caſts a ſhame</l>
                  <l>Vpon the beauty of thy honour'd Name!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O then, my ſoul, take heed to keep thy heart</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> At thy right hand; There, there ſhe will impart</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:158496:31"/>Continuall ſecrets, and direct thy ways</l>
                  <l>In ſacred <hi>Ethicks,</hi> ſweetning out thy days</l>
                  <l>With ſeaſon'd <hi>Knowledge,</hi> knowledge paſt the reach</l>
                  <l>Of black-mouth'd <hi>Error,</hi> ſhall inſtruct and teach</l>
                  <l>Thy tongue wiſe ſilence; Wiſdome when to break</l>
                  <l>Thy cloſed lips, and Judgement how to ſpeak:</l>
                  <l>Shee'l teach thee Chriſtian <hi>Policy,</hi> and how</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> To keep thee ſafe when as thy <hi>Princes</hi> brow</l>
                  <l>Shall threaten death, even when the flame ſhall flye</l>
                  <l>Like horrid <hi>Lightning</hi> from his wrathfull <hi>Eye:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I, but the rage of <hi>Princes</hi> oftentimes</l>
                  <l>Darts <hi>Lightning</hi> at the <hi>Perſon,</hi> not his <hi>Crimes;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And their miſguided will oft times demands</l>
                  <l>Obedience there, where Conſcience countermands.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Take heed, my ſoul; Thou tread'ſt upon the Ice,</l>
                  <l>Be not too vent'rous here, nor too too nice:</l>
                  <l>Ruſh not too bold; thou mayſt as ſoon convince</l>
                  <l>An <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rror in thy Conſcience, as thy <hi>Prince.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To lay commands upon indifferent things,</l>
                  <l>Is a ſole Royalty belongs to Kings.</l>
                  <l>If here thy conſcience doubt, the Book of Life</l>
                  <l>Muſt caſt the balance, and decide the ſtrife:</l>
                  <l>If this way, thy enforc'd obedience then</l>
                  <l>Muſt ſtoop; If that, <hi>Pleaſe rather God then men.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If th' Embers of his rage ſhould chance to lye</l>
                  <l>Rak'd up, or furnace from his angry eye,</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label>
                     <hi>Quit not thy duty:</hi> 'Tis thy part t'aſſwage</l>
                  <l>The jealous flames of his conſuming rage.</l>
                  <l>What, if through <hi>Error</hi> or miſguided will</l>
                  <l>He leaves the way to Good, and cleaves to Ill;</l>
                  <l>Lend him thy <hi>Prayers;</hi> Lament, adviſe, perſwade,</l>
                  <l>Lift not thy hand, nor let thy tongue upbraid</l>
                  <l>His ſacred <hi>Perſon;</hi> Hee's by heav'n appointed</l>
                  <l>To be thy <hi>Prince;</hi> O <hi>touch not heav'ns Anointed.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:158496:31"/>What, if he lend the fulneſſe of his pow'r</l>
                  <l>To thoſe imperious Spirits that devour</l>
                  <l>Subjects like bread, and drinke the loyall blood</l>
                  <l>Of men like water; men, not once allow'd</l>
                  <l>To plead for life; but ſilently ſubſcribe</l>
                  <l>To thoſe that cannot judge without a Bribe?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What, if his power pleaſes to commit</l>
                  <l>His paſt'rall ſtaffe to ſuch as are more fit</l>
                  <l>To kill and eat, or recommend his flocks</l>
                  <l>To ſuch dumb dogs, of whom nor wolfe nor fox</l>
                  <l>Will ſtand in awe, or ſhow their feares by flight,</l>
                  <l>That have not tongues to bark, nor teeth to bite?</l>
                  <l>Rebell not thou, nor in a hoſtile way</l>
                  <l>Accoaſt thy <hi>Prince;</hi> Or ſuffer, or obey.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What, if the Common Favorite of the times</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>6</label>(The Courtly <hi>Fool,</hi> grown great with count'nance) climes</l>
                  <l>Vp to a Lordſhip, when the Man of merit</l>
                  <l>Broke on the wheele of Fortune muſt inherit</l>
                  <l>Nothing but ſcorne and want; and a <hi>poore</hi> name</l>
                  <l>Betraid to pity, and to empty Fame?</l>
                  <l>Be thou thy ſelf, let not thine eye be evill:</l>
                  <l>To a wiſe heart both hills and dales are levell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>17</label> How <hi>happy</hi> is that land, how bleſt the <hi>Nation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe Prince directs by Power, not by <hi>Paſſion?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſacred wiſdome knowes how great a price</l>
                  <l>True vertue beares, and how to puniſh <hi>Vice;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe royall Majeſty, and princely love</l>
                  <l>Can both incorporate, and joyntly move</l>
                  <l>In a ſelf glorious Orbe, and from one Sphear</l>
                  <l>Breathe ſuch rare influence of love, and fear</l>
                  <l>Into the hearts of Men, that all the land</l>
                  <l>Shall cry a <hi>Solomon,</hi> and ſweetly ſtand</l>
                  <l>Rapt with ſweet Peace, and ſacred admiration:</l>
                  <l>How <hi>happy</hi> is that land, how bleſt the <hi>Nation!</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:158496:32"/>
               <head>CAP. II.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>1</hi> Directions for Charitie. <hi>7</hi> Death in life, <hi>9</hi> and the day of judgement in the dayes of youth, are to be thought on.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label> VPon the waters let thy bread be caſt,</l>
                  <l>And thou ſhalt finde it when ſome dayes are paſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> Give lib'rall Almes, for it's unknown to thee</l>
                  <l>How full of wants thy after dayes ſhall be.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>3</label> If clouds be full, will they deny to powr</l>
                  <l>Their fruitfull Bleſſings in a lib'rall ſhow'r?</l>
                  <l>Or North or South, or whereſoere the Tree</l>
                  <l>Shall fall, no queſtion it ſhall fall to thee.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> He that obſerves the wind ſhall never ſow:</l>
                  <l>Who marks the clouds ſhall never reap nor mow.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>5</label> Like as the Embryo's growth within their wombes,</l>
                  <l>Is ſtrange to thee, and how the ſoule becomes</l>
                  <l>The bodies inmate; ev'n ſo all the reſt</l>
                  <l>Of Heavn's high workes are ſtrangers to thy breſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>6</label> Caſt thou thy morning ſeed upon the land,</l>
                  <l>And at the evening hold not back thy hand;</l>
                  <l>For who is he can tell thee which of theſe</l>
                  <l>Shall proſper beſt, or bring the beſt encreaſe?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>7</label>'Tis true, the light is ſweet, and every one</l>
                  <l>Takes pleaſure in the world-rejoycing Sunne:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>8</label> But who lives many joyfull yeares, if he</l>
                  <l>But count how long his after ſhades ſhall be</l>
                  <l>In earths darke boſome, how can he refraine</l>
                  <l>To think theſe ſhort-liv'd flattering pleaſures vaine?</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>9</label> Rejoyce, ô young man, in thy youthfull wayes;</l>
                  <l>Let thy heart cheer thee in thy youthfull dayes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:158496:32"/>Delight thine eyes, thy heart, and take thy way;</l>
                  <l>But know that heavens accompt will finde a day.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>10</label> Then baniſh falſ-ey'd mirth: Be diſpoſſeſt</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe lewd fires that ſo inflame thy breſt;</l>
                  <l>For childhood, youth, and all their joyes remain</l>
                  <l>But for a ſeaſon, and they all are vain.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="soliloquy">
               <head>SOLILOQUIE II.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SO now my ſoul, thy wiſdome-ſeaſon'd breſt</l>
                  <l>May eat and drink, and labour, and digeſt</l>
                  <l>Thy carefull morſels, and with holy mirth</l>
                  <l>Diſperſe the clouds of melancholy earth:</l>
                  <l>Now maiſt thou ſit beneath thy cluſtred <hi>Vine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And preſſe thy Grapes, and drinke thy frolick wine</l>
                  <l>In ſoft and plenteous <hi>Peace,</hi> and leave to morrow</l>
                  <l>To beare the burden of her ſelfe-borne ſorrow:</l>
                  <l>Now maiſt thou walke ſecure from all thoſe threats</l>
                  <l>of peeviſh Fortune, and the ſly deceits</l>
                  <l>Of flattering pleaſure: Plenty cannot drown</l>
                  <l>Thine eyes in mirth, nor miſery caſt thee down:</l>
                  <l>If the blew Rafters of the falling skies</l>
                  <l>Should leave their ſpangled Manſion, and ſurpriſe</l>
                  <l>Thy feeble ſtrength, well may their ruines ſmite thee,</l>
                  <l>And grinde thy clod to duſt, but not affright thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What want'ſt thou then, my ſoule, that may augment</l>
                  <l>The reall happineſſe of a true content?</l>
                  <l>What vertue's wanting now, whoſe abſence may</l>
                  <l>Encourage boldfac'd vanity to betray</l>
                  <l>Thy even-ſpunne dayes to ſorrow; or occaſion</l>
                  <l>Thy faire-contriv'd deſignes to taſt vexation?</l>
                  <l>Wouldſt thou have Honor? thou enjoyſt it: Treaſure?</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt it: wouldſt thou gain the greater pleaſure</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:158496:33"/>Of a true noble Spouſe; whoſe life may ſhow</l>
                  <l>Vertues rare quinteſſence? Thou haſt that too:</l>
                  <l>Wouldſt thou have hopefull Sonnes to crowne thy Laſt</l>
                  <l>With Peace and Honor? Such rare Sonnes thou haſt:</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Princes</hi> favour? Or thy peoples love?</l>
                  <l>All this thou haſt: Wiſdome in things above?</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt it: Knowledge in theſe Toyes beneath?</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt it: Skill in th' <hi>Arts?</hi> or curious breath</l>
                  <l>Of whiſpering <hi>State?</hi> All this thou haſt: Where, then,</l>
                  <l>Shall thy new wiſhes fix, Rare Man of men?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, but my ſoule, one good is wanting ſtill</l>
                  <l>To ſumme a full Perfection, and to fill</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Cruiſe</hi> with happineſſe: which if poſſeſt,</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt a <hi>Diademe,</hi> crownes all the reſt:</l>
                  <l>Hadſt thou the <hi>tongues of men,</hi> and couldſt thou break</l>
                  <l>Thy lips in <hi>Oracles;</hi> Or couldſt thou ſpeak</l>
                  <l>The dialects of <hi>Angels</hi> when they ſing</l>
                  <l>Their ſacred <hi>Canzons</hi> to their ſoveraigne King,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A tinkling Cymball,</hi> or the hideous ſounds</l>
                  <l>Of diſcompoſed <hi>diſcords,</hi> or the <hi>Rounds</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of frolick midnight madneſſe would requite</l>
                  <l>Thy wilde attention with as much delight,</l>
                  <l>And breathe as ſweetly in the <hi>Almighties</hi> eare</l>
                  <l>If heart-rejoycing <hi>Charity</hi> be not there:</l>
                  <l>Hadſt thou what ſtrength the <hi>Parnaſſean</hi> Muſe</l>
                  <l>Can bleſſe thy fancy with, or heaven infuſe;</l>
                  <l>Hadſt thou a <hi>Faith to make the mountaines fly</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In the vaſt <hi>Orbe,</hi> like Atomes in thine eye;</l>
                  <l>Leſſe then thoſe Atomes would thy Faith appeare,</l>
                  <l>If faith-confirming <hi>Charity</hi> be not there:</l>
                  <l>Shouldſt thou, to purchaſe heaven, renounce thy Right</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>all thy goods,</hi> and turne an <hi>Anchorite;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or ſhould thy courage, to deſerve the name</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Martyr,</hi> give thy body to the flame,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:158496:33"/>When that blood pleads, heav'n will not lend an eare</l>
                  <l>If heav'n-engaging <hi>Charity</hi> be not there.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since then, my ſoul, both Faith and Works lie dead</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label> If <hi>Charity</hi> fail, be wiſe, and <hi>caſt thy bread</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Upon the Waters;</hi> As the Waters runne</l>
                  <l>Deal thou thy dole, untill thy dole be done.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Man is Gods Husbandry;</hi> If then the Plough</l>
                  <l>Of carefull want hath ſtruck the furrow'd Brow,</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>6</label> And make it fit for ſeed; <hi>Hold not thy hand;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He robs himſelf that faintly ſows the Land:</l>
                  <l>Stay not for ſhowres; The ſoile, if overflowne,</l>
                  <l>Will drown thy ſeed-corn, and return thee none:</l>
                  <l>Let not ſome weeds diſcourage thee to ſow.</l>
                  <l>The Plough will root them up, or if they grow</l>
                  <l>Too ſturdy for the Coulters point to kill,</l>
                  <l>Fear not thy harveſt; A hard Winter will.</l>
                  <l>Caſt not lank grain upon too lean a ground,</l>
                  <l>Fair Crops from off all Corn are rarely found.</l>
                  <l>Sow cloſely what thou ſow'ſt, and leaſt in ſight,</l>
                  <l>The eyes of Doves will make thy harvest light:</l>
                  <l>But ſtay! Thou mayſt ſurcharge as well as ſterve</l>
                  <l>The ſoile; But wiſe men know what ſeed will ſerve:</l>
                  <l>Thy work thus wiſely done; what, then, remains?</l>
                  <l>Give Heav'n the glory, and expect the Gains.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XII.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>1</hi> The Creatour rs to be remembred in due time. <hi>8</hi> The Preachers care to edifie. <hi>13</hi> The feare of God is the chief Antidote of vanity.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label> REmember thy Creator in thy prime</l>
                  <l>Of preſent youth, before the black-mouth'd time</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:158496:34"/>Of ſullen age approach; before the day</l>
                  <l>Thy dying pleaſures find a dull decay;</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> Before the Sun, and Moon, and Stars appear</l>
                  <l>Dark in thy Microcoſmal Hemiſphear;</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>3</label> Before the Clouds of ſorrows multiply,</l>
                  <l>And hide the Cryſtall of thy gloomy sky;</l>
                  <l>Before the Keepers of thy crazy Tow'r</l>
                  <l>I'e palſie-ſtricken, and thy men of pow'r</l>
                  <l>Sink as they march, and Grinders ceaſe to grind</l>
                  <l>Diſtaſtfull bread, and windows are grown blind.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> Then ſhall the Caſtles two-leafd gates be barr'd</l>
                  <l>When as the Milſtones language is not heard;</l>
                  <l>The horn-mouth Belman ſhal affright thy ſlumbers,</l>
                  <l>Thy untun'd ear ſhall loath harmonious numbers:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>5</label> Each obvious mole-hill ſhall encreaſe thy fears,</l>
                  <l>And carefull ſnow ſhall blanch thy falling hairs;</l>
                  <l>A fly ſhall load thy ſhoulders: Thy deſire</l>
                  <l>And all thy bed-rid paſſions ſhall expire.</l>
                  <l>Pale death's at hand, and mourners come to meet</l>
                  <l>Thy tear-bedabled fun'rals in the Street.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>6</label> Then ſhall the ſinews ſilver cord be los'd</l>
                  <l>Thy brains gold bowle be broke: The undiſpos'd</l>
                  <l>And idle liver's ruby fountain dri'd;</l>
                  <l>The blouds Meandring Ciſterns unſuppli'd.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>7</label> Then ſhall the duſt her duſt, to duſt deliver,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſpirit ſhall return to God the Giver.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>8</label> Whereto th'Eccleſiaſtick thus replies,</l>
                  <l>All, all is vain, and vaineſt vanities.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>9</label> Becauſe his true repentant ſoul was wiſe,</l>
                  <l>He read this wiſdome-lecture, did adviſe</l>
                  <l>And ſearch the Fountain, whence he did convay</l>
                  <l>The fruitfull ſtreams in a Proverbiall way.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>10</label> He ſought and found ſuch words, which had the might</l>
                  <l>To entermingle profit with delight;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:158496:34"/>And what his spirit-prompted pen did write</l>
                  <l>Was truth it ſelf, and moſt exact upright.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>11</label> The wiſe mans words are like to Goads, that doe</l>
                  <l>Stir up the drowzy, and ſpur up the ſlow:</l>
                  <l>And like to nailes to be made faſt and driv'n</l>
                  <l>By hands to th'hearts of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſent down from heav'n.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>12</label> Make uſe, my Son, of what this hand hath penn'd,</l>
                  <l>There is no end of Pamphlets to no end;</l>
                  <l>Theſe tire the fleſh, and after age is ſpent,</l>
                  <l>They breathe ſome knowledge, but no true content.</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>13</label> Mark then the ground where the main building</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fear thou thy God, Obſerve his juſt Commands.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Within the limits of this ſacred Ground ſtands,</l>
                  <l>Mans duty lies; true Happineſſe is found:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>14</label> No work ſhall paſſe untri'd: No hand hath done</l>
                  <l>What ſhall not plead at heav'ns Tribunall Throne:</l>
                  <l>All ſecrets good and bad attend his Eye;</l>
                  <l>His Eyes behold where day could never prye.</l>
               </lg>
               <q>Deus his quoque finem.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="soliloquy">
               <head>SOLILOQUIE XII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOw launch, my ſoul, into this Sea of Tears;</l>
                  <l>Fear ſtorms and Rocks, yet ſmile upon thy fears;</l>
                  <l>Weigh Anchor; Hoiſt thy weather-beaten Sailes;</l>
                  <l>The Tides run ſmooth; The wind breaths proſp'rous Gales.</l>
                  <l>Tridented <hi>Neptune</hi> now hath ſtruck a peace</l>
                  <l>With full-mouth'd <hi>Aeolus,</hi> and the wars ſurceaſe:</l>
                  <l>They ſound a parley, and begin to treat,</l>
                  <l>And Sea-green <hi>Triton</hi> ſounds a ſhrill Retreat.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:158496:35"/>March new, my ſoul, through <hi>Hadadrimmons</hi> Vale</l>
                  <l>Without a tear; or if thou muſt bewaile,</l>
                  <l>Mourn for vain Earth, and drop in alms, one teare</l>
                  <l>For him that finds no happineſſe but there.</l>
                  <l>Now mayſt thou trample on the <hi>Aſp,</hi> and tread</l>
                  <l>on the <hi>young Lyon,</hi> and th' <hi>old Dragons</hi> head;</l>
                  <l>Wiſdome ſhall guide thee, Love ſhall circumcloſe thee,</l>
                  <l>That fraud ſhall not beguile, or force oppoſe thee.</l>
                  <l>Thy Prince ſhall honor thee, thy Peers embrace thee;</l>
                  <l>No Crime ſhall ſhame thee, and no tongue diſgrace thee;</l>
                  <l>The rich ſhall rev'rence thee, the poor ſhall bleſſe thee;</l>
                  <l>Wrath ſhall not over-rule, nor pride oppreſſe thee;</l>
                  <l>Thy want ſhall not afflict, nor wealth betray thee,</l>
                  <l>This ſhall not puffe thee up, nor that diſmay thee:</l>
                  <l>Pleaſure ſhall not enſnare, nor pains torment thee,</l>
                  <l>This ſhall not make thee ſad, nor that repent thee.</l>
                  <l>Bleſt ſhall thy Labours be, and ſweet thy Reſt;</l>
                  <l>Bleſt ſhall thy Thoughts be, and thy Actions bleſt;</l>
                  <l>Bleſt in thy peace, and bleſt in thy promotion;</l>
                  <l>Bleſt in thy ſports, and bleſt in thy devotion;</l>
                  <l>Bleſt in thy loſſes, bleſt in thy encreaſes;</l>
                  <l>Bleſt in thy health, and bleſt in thy diſeaſes;</l>
                  <l>Bleſt in thy Knowledge, bleſt in thy Corrections;</l>
                  <l>Bleſt in thy Soul, and bleſt in thy Affections.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O then my ſoul, let thy Affections flow</l>
                  <l>In ſtreams of love to Him that lov'd thee ſo;</l>
                  <l>Let not his high-priz'd benefits depart</l>
                  <l>From thy remembrance, grave them in thy heart</l>
                  <l>With Tools of Adamant, that they may laſt</l>
                  <l>To after times, that when thy days be paſt,</l>
                  <l>Thy well-inſtructed children may emblaze</l>
                  <l>Thy Makers goodneſſe to the laſt of days.</l>
                  <l>Bleſſe thou the Lord, my ſoul; Let thy whole frame,</l>
                  <l>And all within thee magnifie that Name</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:158496:35"/>That bleſt thee ſo; Bleſſe thou the Lord, my ſoul,</l>
                  <l>Report his precious favour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and enroll</l>
                  <l>His numerous mercies in thy gratefull breſt:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>1</label>
                     <hi>Remember thy Creator;</hi> O proteſt</l>
                  <l>His praiſes to the world, and let thy tongue</l>
                  <l>Make him the ſubject of thy youthfull ſong;</l>
                  <l>Give him the firſtlings of thy ſtrength, even than</l>
                  <l>When fading Childehood ſeeks to ripen man</l>
                  <l>Vpon thy downy cheeks; when vigour trains</l>
                  <l>The ſparkling blood through thy Meandring veins;</l>
                  <l>Before thy flowing marrow ſhall foment</l>
                  <l>Thy luſt full fires; before the falſe content</l>
                  <l>Of frothy pleaſures ſhall begin t'invite.</l>
                  <l>Thy fond Affections to a vain delight.</l>
                  <l>Then, then, my ſoul, whilſt thy ſupplies are freſh</l>
                  <l>And ſtrong, wage war with thy rebellious fteſh;</l>
                  <l>Gird up thy loyns, and march, ſpare neither ſweat</l>
                  <l>Nor blood, take courage, ſtrike, ſubdue, defeat:</l>
                  <l>Sing a triumphant ſong; ſing <hi>Io Paean,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Adorn thy brows with Palm, and again ſing <hi>Io Paean.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Take time while time ſhall ſerve; 'tis thine to day,</l>
                  <l>But ſecret danger ſtill attends delay.</l>
                  <l>Doe while thou mayſt; To day has eagle wings,</l>
                  <l>And who can tell what change to morrow brings?</l>
                  <l>Advantage waſts, and ſtrength of body wears,</l>
                  <l>Life has no Leaſe; and Youth, no Tearm for years:</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>3</label> When creeping <hi>Age</hi> ſhall quench thy ſprightly fires,</l>
                  <l>And breathe cold Winter on thy <hi>chill deſires,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> What fire ſhall burn thy offerings? O what praiſe</l>
                  <l>Can iſſue forth from cold decrepit dayes?</l>
                  <l>When ebbing bloods neap-tides ſhall ſtrike thy <hi>lims</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With trembling Palſies; when dry Age bedims</l>
                  <l>The <hi>optick ſunſhine</hi> of thy bed-rid days,</l>
                  <l>What boots thy cold, thy Paralytick praiſe?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:158496:36"/>When ſecret Vlcers ſhall attaint thy breath</l>
                  <l>With fumes more noyſome then the ſinks of death,</l>
                  <l>What pleaſure ſhall thy great Creator raiſe</l>
                  <l>From thy breath-tainted, and unſav'ry praiſe?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come then, my ſoul, Rouze up thy dull deſire,</l>
                  <l>And quicken thy faint coals of ſacred fire,</l>
                  <l>That lie rak'd up in th'Embers of thy fleſh;</l>
                  <l>Fetch breath from heaven, and with that breath refreſh</l>
                  <l>Thy glim'ring ſparks: Brook not the leaſt delay,</l>
                  <l>Embers grow cold, and ſparks will ſoon decay.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="obituary">
            <head>In obitum viri clariſſimi, at que ingenioſiſſimi Poëtae, <hi>Franciſci</hi> QUARLES, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Cygne felix, ocyùs avola,</l>
               <l>Cantator ales, cùm neque jam vada</l>
               <l>Ripis ſuperſint, nec quietae</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Purus aquae fluat (ecce!)rivus;</l>
               <l>Fontes nec ipſi: Sanguine, ſanguine</l>
               <l>(Heu!) cuncta manant quod mare civicae</l>
               <l>Non decoloravêre caedes?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ipſa, vides, rubet Hippocrene.</l>
               <l>Et quis poëtis jam locus aut latex?</l>
               <l>Quae lympha Muſis? cùm cruor undique.</l>
               <l>Hinc, hinc migrandum, nibibemus</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Purpureas Heliconis undas.</l>
               <l>At ô Camaenarum &amp; dolor &amp; decus,</l>
               <l>Tu ſi recedas, quis tua funera</l>
               <l>Cantabit, ô divine vates?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Que moritur moriente Phoebus.</l>
               <l>Quiſquámne fundet jam <hi>querulum</hi> melos?</l>
               <l>(Falſum nec omen nominis hoc tui;)</l>
               <l>Moeſtúmve panget carmen arte,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Melpomenes citharâ canorus?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:158496:36"/>Quis ſerta coelo jam dabit? aut pium</l>
               <l>Emb lema texet floribus ingenî?</l>
               <l>Quis ſymbolorum voce pictâ</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnà oculos animúm<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> paſcet?</l>
               <l>Quis melle puro jam, calami potens,</l>
               <l>Condîta promet dia poëmata?</l>
               <l>Aut funditabit, grande, ſacro</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Enthea metra calens furore?</l>
               <l>Quis ſanctitatem nectare carminis</l>
               <l>Tinctam propinans, digna Deo canet?</l>
               <l>Coelúm<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> verſu claudet omni,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Atque fidem fidibus ſonabit?</l>
               <l>Tu nempe litem, ſi pote, publicam</l>
               <l>Compeſcuiſſes dulciſonis modis,</l>
               <l>Ni laeva nobis mens, &amp; orbi</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Harmoni am reducem dediſſes.</l>
               <l>Mollîſſe magnos tu poteras duces,</l>
               <l>Feras ut Orpheus flexanimis ſonis;</l>
               <l>Pacémque pulſam, júſque mundo, ac</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Eurydicen retuliſſe cantu.</l>
               <l>Per te coîſſent diſsita pectora,</l>
               <l>Per te coîſsent diruta moenia:</l>
               <l>Tu ſolus Amphion peritus</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vel lapides ſociare plectro.</l>
               <l>Poſtquàm hoc negatum; ponere noveras</l>
               <l>Emblema ſaltem flebile ſeculi,</l>
               <l>Belli<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>: noſtris ſed nec ullum</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Par Hieroglyphicum ruinis.</l>
               <l>Quando ergo te nec terra capit, tuis</l>
               <l>Nec digna Mnſis; I, pete coelites,</l>
               <l>Intér<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> coetus Angelorum</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Perpetuum modulare carmen.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Jacobus Duport, Graecae Linguae Profeſſor Cantab.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:158496:37"/>
            <head>An Elegie upon the famous Poet FRANCIS QUARLES.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IS <hi>Quarles</hi> dead? his active spirit flown?</l>
               <l>And none to lend a teare, a ſigh, a groan,</l>
               <l>For the worlds loſſe? me thinks at leaſt alleyes</l>
               <l>(Since tongues can not) ſhould weep large Elegies.</l>
               <l>Expect no Muſes; for they at his death</l>
               <l>Compaſsionate, loſt their Poetique breath.</l>
               <l>Expect no marble Tombe; he's above fate;</l>
               <l>His name (if Learning live) ſhall know no date:</l>
               <l>His iſſue ſhall ſurvive poſterity,</l>
               <l>This age and th'next, and ſo t'eternity.</l>
               <l>Peruſe his <hi>Phanſies,</hi> and his <hi>Emblems</hi> wrapt;</l>
               <l>And ſee <hi>S. Paul</hi> into the third heav'ns rapt:</l>
               <l>Or elſe ſome Cherubim ſent down from thence</l>
               <l>T'unfold heav'ns Myſteries in heav'ns Eloquence.</l>
               <l>A Poet-ſaint he was, in him each line</l>
               <l>Speakes out at large rare Poet, choyce Divine.</l>
               <l>His meſſage done, he flyes unto his Maker,</l>
               <l>Of what he told us here, to be partaker.</l>
               <l>His priſon'd ſoul was ſo harmonious here;</l>
               <l>Now looſe, what Muſicke, think you, makes ſhe there!</l>
               <l>She wept, then ſung; now ſung, 'gaine wept in rime:</l>
               <l>Her Reſt now know no ſtop, her joy no time.</l>
               <l>Her Phanſy Viſion is, ſhe now doth live</l>
               <l>With Angels food, knowledge intuitive.</l>
               <l>By Emblems darke to ſpell the Deitie</l>
               <l>She taught before, now ſees Divinitie.</l>
               <l>But ſtay, my Muſe: the clouds doe interpoſe</l>
               <l>Twixt thee and her; 'tis better for thee cloſe,</l>
               <l>Then pierce, or peep too farre. Phoebus is ſet;</l>
               <l>Th'haſt pay'd thy tribute light, thy tribute heat,</l>
               <l>Sigh out the reſt: or wouldſt thou to him go,</l>
               <l>Thy Love, thy Life? Goe be entombed too. <hi>R. Stable.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
